<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>suffering on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/suffering/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (suffering)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:42 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/suffering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The conviction that they had been chosen by the only god that exists went through its most crucial test in the Exile &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;../babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/&#34;&gt;see: lament&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;. Conquest and exile interacted with the core Jewish tenet of the chosen people, destined by Yahweh for the lead role among all the peoples of the world. This gave rise to a new genre of prophecy, initiated by Jeremiah even while the monarchical state was in the process of collapsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What emerged was a consolidation and reinterpretation of what had gone before. [&amp;hellip;] Defeat and suffering were interpreted as divine retribution for moral and legal transgressions, sin codified as central to the divine scheme. They were suffering the consequences of neglecting their side of the covenant with Yahweh. But—and here was the new emphasis—Yahweh was a merciful and wise god: he would use their sin and suffering to teach his people—&lt;em&gt;and through them all human beings&lt;/em&gt;—a new way of thought and practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of this [&amp;hellip;came&amp;hellip;] central ideas about the divine nature and the human condition. Defeat and disaster were explained in terms not, as in the Greek historians, of human expectations, interests, and conflicts, but in terms of a divine design for humanity. They created &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; counter-culture of the oppressed, making themselves superior in the divine scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was more than this: Jeremiah prophesied a new covenant in which Yahweh would give the people ‘law within them and write it on their hearts&amp;hellip;No longer need they teach one another to know the Lord; all of them, high and low alike, shall know me’ (Jer. 31: 31–4). This was a revolution within a revolution: it meant, obviously, that every individual Israelite would know Yahweh for himself/herself. The law was internalized. The implication of this for individualism and democracy are prodigious and clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israeite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>