<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ashoka on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/ashoka/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (ashoka)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:30 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/ashoka/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Buddhism - Overview</title>
      <link>/posts/buddhism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:30 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/buddhism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two people key to its spread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;siddhartha-gautama&#34;&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born mid-sixth century BCE in the foothills of the Himalaya Mountains, in what is today southern Nepal, the son of a ruling kshatriya family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a family, left his family, meditated under a tree, achieved enlightenment, spent the rest of his life preaching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His ideas can be viewed as a reformist form of Brahmanism, designed to transfer responsibility from the priests to the individual, much as the sixteenth century German monk Martin Luther saw his ideas as a reformation of Christianity. Siddhartha accepted the concept of reincarnation and the role of karma as a means of influencing the movement of individual souls up and down the scale of life. Nirvana, the extinction of selfhood and reunion with the Great World Soul, is likened to a dreamless sleep, rather than the Christian concept of heavenly salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four noble truths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life is suffering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suffering is caused by desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end suffering is to end desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end desire is to avoid the extremes of a life of vulgar materialism and to follow the Middle Path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Middle Path: right knowledge, purpose, speech, conduct, occupation, effort, awareness, meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All human beings can aspire to Nirvana as a result of their behaviour in this life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siddharta Gautama died in 480 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ashoka&#34;&gt;Ashoka&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Converted to Buddhism in the third century BCE, and sent Buddhist missionaries throughout India, and ordered the erection of stone pillars with official edicts and Buddhist inscriptions to instruct people in the proper way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashoka died in 232 BCE, after which the Mauryan empire began to fragment into separate states - in 183 BCE, India reverted to disunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India History</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:02:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ca. 2600–1900 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harappan civilization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ca. 1500 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrival of the Aryans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ca. 560-480 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life of Gautama Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;326 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invasion of India by Alexander the Great&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;324 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauryan Dynasty founded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;324-301 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reign of Chandragupta Maurya&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;269-232 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reign of Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;183 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collapse of Mauryan Dynasty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the time of the Mauryans, Aryan buildings had been constructed of wood. With the rise of the empire, stone began to be used as artisans arrived in India seeking employment after the destruction of the Persian Empire by Alexander. Many of these stone carvers accepted the patronage of Emperor Ashoka, who used them to spread Buddhist ideas throughout the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>