<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>solon on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/solon/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (solon)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:22:03 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/solon/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Athenian Political Background</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/athenian-political-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:22:03 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/athenian-political-background/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;consolidation-of-power-through-the-archaic-period&#34;&gt;Consolidation of power through the Archaic Period&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristocratic monopolization of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;elected offices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the city council, &lt;em&gt;Areopagus&lt;/em&gt;, which was composed of former office holders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;archonship&#34;&gt;Archonship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the seventh century BCE, executive authority in Athens lay entirely with the nine &lt;em&gt;archons&lt;/em&gt; presiding over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a high court with influence over hearing of cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appointed by the Areopagus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one year term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime membership in the Areopagus after&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome of inequality: a significant proportion of the population fell into slavery through debt, while struggles among aristocratic families destabilized the government and fomented cycles of revenge killings. This situation eventually inspired the Athenians&amp;rsquo; first attempt to promulgate a set of written laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;establishing-democracy&#34;&gt;Establishing democracy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drakon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peisistratos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spartan-sponsored oligarchy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleisthenes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drakon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Also known as Draco, Drako. The first recorded legislator of Athens, replacing the prevailing system of oral law and blood feud with the first written constitution of Athens in 621 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His laws were harsh, hence &amp;ldquo;draconian&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
A poet elected in 594 BCE as the sole archon for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solon’s legendary political and economic reforms laid the foundations for the later development of Athenian democracy. He forbade the practice of debt slavery and set up a fund to buy back Athenian slaves who had been sold abroad. He encouraged the cultivation of olives and grapes, thus spurring cash-crop farming and urban industries such as oil and wine production, and the manufacture of pottery storage jars and decorative drinking cups. He also broadened rights of political participation and set up courts in which a range of citizens served as jurors and to which any Athenian might appeal. He based eligibility for political office on property qualifications, thus making it possible for someone not born into the aristocracy to gain access to power. Moreover, he convened an Athenian assembly, the &lt;em&gt;ekklesia&lt;/em&gt; and gave it the right to elect archons. Now all free-born Athenian men over the age of eighteen could participate in government. Even those who were not eligible for citizenship were able to see the workings of government for themselves, since the assembled citizens met on the slopes of the Pnyx, a hill visible from the central marketplace and overlooked by the sacred precincts of the Acropolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solon’s reforms were not immediately accepted. The aristocracy thought them too radical; the people of the demos, not radical enough. In the resulting generation of turmoil&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peisistratos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
546 BCE: An aristocrat named Peisistratos establishes himself as tyrant (see: &lt;a href=&#34;../tyranny-in-ancient-greece/&#34;&gt;Tyranny in Ancient Greece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat ironically, Peisistratos proceeds to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;institute Solon&amp;rsquo;s reforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;launch a massive campaign of public works projects, including the collection and condification of Homer&amp;rsquo;s epics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;crush dissent mercilessly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ultimately, strengthen the political role of the demos and so remain a popular ruler until his death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His sons were less able to control the various factions that threatened their rule; one was assassinated and the other was ousted with the help of the Spartans in 510 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spartan-sponsored-oligarchy&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spartan-sponsored oligarchy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleisthenes&lt;/strong&gt;
Two generations of increasing access to power had left the Athenian demos with a taste for self-government, and a group of commoners rallied behind Cleisthenes, an aristocrat who championed the cause of the demos. Once voted in as archon in 508/7 BCE, Cleisthenes took steps to limit aristocratic power by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reorganizing the Athenian population into ten voting districts, hence suppressing traditional loyalties tied to certain aristocratic families&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strengthening Athenian assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extending democracy to the local level throughout Attica&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing ostracism - whereby Athenians could decide each year whether they wanted to banish someone for a decade and, if so, whom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleisthenes hoped that with this, the demos could 1. prevent the return of a tyrant 2. quell factional strife if civil war seemed imminent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;by-500-bce&#34;&gt;By 500 BCE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The political struggles of the sixth century had given Athens a far more populist character than any other Greek polis and had strengthened its institutions of government. In the meantime, Athens had become the principal exporter of olive oil, wine, and pottery in the Greek world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;persian-wars&#34;&gt;Persian Wars&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: in the decades before the Persian Wars, political reforms in Athens had continued to encourage further experiments in democracy, including the practice of selecting major officeholders by lot. Only one key position was now filled by traditional voting: the office of &lt;em&gt;strategos&lt;/em&gt;, or general. And because a man could be elected stratgos year after year, this office became the career goal of Athens&amp;rsquo;s most ambitious figures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Themistocles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When the Athenians discovered a rich vein of silver ore in the Attic countryside, Themistocles persuaded them not to divide the windfall among themselves (the customary practice) but to finance a fleet of 200 triremes - state-of-the-art warships - thereby transforming Athens into the preeminent naval power of the Greek World&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cimon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;hellip;just in time to confront a new Persian onslaught, as Cimon led the Delian league to victories in 470s and 460s BCE. But Cimon also used the league to punish poleis who tried to opt out of membership, suppressing revolts by force of arms and turning the league into an instrument of Athenian policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 462-461 BCE, Cimon was ostracised by his rival&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pericles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;hellip;an aristocrat from one of Athens&amp;rsquo;s richest families, who rose to strategos on the enfranchisement of the thetes, the lowest class of free men and the rowers of the triremes, as his political platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He oversaw:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a foreign policy oriented away from cooperation with Sparta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reforms that gave every citizen the right to propose and amend legislation, not just to vote yes or no in the citizen assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an average day&amp;rsquo;s wage for attendance in the assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and through the latter measures, thetes and other free men of modest means becoming a dominant force in politics, and loyal to the man who made that dominance possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the ambitions of Pericles, this populist program glorified Athens through an ambitious scheme of public building and lavish festivals honoring the gods, especially Athena. Personally, too, Pericles was a generous patron of the arts and sciences, attracting the greatest minds and talents of the day to Athens. His popularity, combined with his charisma and his promotion of the Athenians’ sense of superiority, ensured his reelection as strategos for the next three decades. During these years Athens flourished, but it also alienated much of the Greek world by its arrogance and aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>