<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>confucianism on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/confucianism/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (confucianism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 02:43:21 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/confucianism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Confucianism and Population Density</title>
      <link>/posts/confucianism-population-density/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 02:43:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/confucianism-population-density/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Li, in Confucianism, is a formalization of the philosophy behind the clearly sanctioned rules and behaviour that underpin Asian societies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High yields have always supported large populations in monsoon Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The states and empires of monsoon Asia were built consistently on their common peasant base of intensive, high-yield agriculture, which provided the great bulk of revenues, the manpower for armies, and the highly structured social order. [&amp;hellip;] The village worlds were largely self-governing and self-regulating, thanks to the family system, the kin network, and the basic social institutions common to the area as a whole, but they formed the essential foundation for the building and maintenance of empires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Murphey, Rhoads. &lt;em&gt;A History of Asia&lt;/em&gt;. Routledge, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Han Confucianism</title>
      <link>/posts/han-confucianism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:55:49 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/han-confucianism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background: unification and centralization by Qin provided a milieu in which the gentlemanly culture of Confucianism could flourish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Confucianism was thus a conflation of earlier Confucianism, mystical cosmology, and authoritarian statism (CHC i. 107, 652). The Zhou notion of monarchy had been transformed, but the nature and extent of the change was not apparent in the language used. The ‘institutional framework’ was and remained a ‘legalist autocracy’ (Wang and Chang 1986: 12). But the state could now afford to be benevolent. Chinese historians have called it ‘outside Confucian, inside legalist’ (Zhengyuan Fu 1996: 8). As Bodde put it, ‘it is the Legalist/Confucian symbiosis evolved during the Han, with administrative controls at the top merging into self-administered behavioural standards below, that gave to the Chinese state the necessary combination of firmness and flexibility that enabled it to survive’ (CHC i. 90).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confucianism - Overview</title>
      <link>/posts/confucianism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 07:06:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/confucianism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Confucius: 551 - 479 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;li-and-ren&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Li&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ren&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Li&lt;/em&gt;: ritual, custom, decorum, propriety, ethics - a concept extended from a code of conduct and traditional conventions of social intercourse to embrace a &amp;ldquo;broad range of political activities, such as personnel policy, [and] proper handling of rewards and punishments&amp;rdquo;, so that it came to comprise the &amp;ldquo;entire way of governing&amp;rdquo;. Interpretation of the ethical and societal norms of &lt;em&gt;li&lt;/em&gt; was the focus of Confucian thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ren&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lsquo;to overcome the self and turn to &lt;em&gt;li&lt;/em&gt;. The inner rationale that motivates people to observe &lt;em&gt;li&lt;/em&gt;. The humaneness that legitimizes political order (as interpreted by Mengzi, Confucius&amp;rsquo;s disciple). Confucius insisted that humaneness was the fundamental norm not only ofhuman conduct, but of political conduct and civilized government. It laid down both the goal and the methods of politics; it stipulated a harmonious society in which the virtuous lead by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Confucius, government works best when the ruler is humane; the praxis was government by consensus - Heaven looking out from the little people, which enlightened paternalism is needed to lead, teach, and treat well. Persuasion is better than coercion. Confucius saw violence as the break- down of politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confucianism saw the state as a family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implementations&#34;&gt;Implementations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../han-confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Han Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>