<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dharma on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/dharma/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (dharma)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 06:12:48 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/dharma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dharma vs Artha; Morality vs Practicality</title>
      <link>/posts/dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 06:12:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dharma: ethics, duty, morality, virtue, social order
Artha: defined by Kautilya as &amp;ldquo;the subsistence of men&amp;rdquo; or the &amp;ldquo;land supplied with men&amp;rdquo; - political interest/necessity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conflict-of-morality-and-political-survival&#34;&gt;Conflict of morality and political survival&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A working out of the conflict between dharma and artha, explored in the section of the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; known as the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gita&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the eve of the final battle, the god Krishna gave Arjuna a transcendent justification of the doctrine of karma. Arjuna was in a quandary: ‘facing us in the field of battle are teachers, fathers and sons&amp;hellip;These I do not wish to slay, even if I myself am slain’. To this Krishna replies: ‘if any man thinks he slays, and if another thinks he is slain, neither knows the ways of truth. The Eternal in man cannot kill: the Eternal in man cannot die&amp;hellip;But to forgo this fight for righteousness is to forgo thy duty and honour: it is to fall into transgression’ (1: 34–5; 2:19, 33). By doing one’s caste duty here and now, therefore—in Arjuna’s case, as a warrior—whatever the consequences, one will acquire benefits through karma in one’s next life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a unique resolution to the conflict between morality and practicality. It avoids the Machiavellian move of denying the validity of moral norms. It implies a statist sense of duty to the public order comparable to what we find in Roman tradition (where Brutus allows the execution of his own son).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:39:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social hierarchy: classical texts specified &lt;em&gt;varna&lt;/em&gt;, a system of four classes in society; this was instantiated into the caste system, &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;, where people are born into a clan (&lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;) that specifies social and economic duty, and requirements for endogamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s thought that this class system was introduced by the Aryans, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-history/&#34;&gt;when they first arrived in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophies that emerged from this background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview/&#34;&gt;Brahmanism&lt;/a&gt;, which later developed into Hinduism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of which were underwritten by the concept of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; - the sum/worth of one&amp;rsquo;s actions in life that decide one&amp;rsquo;s fate in their next life, and in brahmanism, this is accumulated through carrying out &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; - ethics, duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/&#34;&gt;Dharma vs. Artha, Morality vs. Practicality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>