<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ancient india on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/ancient-india/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (ancient india)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 06:12:48 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/ancient-india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dharma vs Artha; Morality vs Practicality</title>
      <link>/posts/dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 06:12:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dharma: ethics, duty, morality, virtue, social order
Artha: defined by Kautilya as &amp;ldquo;the subsistence of men&amp;rdquo; or the &amp;ldquo;land supplied with men&amp;rdquo; - political interest/necessity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conflict-of-morality-and-political-survival&#34;&gt;Conflict of morality and political survival&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A working out of the conflict between dharma and artha, explored in the section of the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; known as the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad Gita&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the eve of the final battle, the god Krishna gave Arjuna a transcendent justification of the doctrine of karma. Arjuna was in a quandary: ‘facing us in the field of battle are teachers, fathers and sons&amp;hellip;These I do not wish to slay, even if I myself am slain’. To this Krishna replies: ‘if any man thinks he slays, and if another thinks he is slain, neither knows the ways of truth. The Eternal in man cannot kill: the Eternal in man cannot die&amp;hellip;But to forgo this fight for righteousness is to forgo thy duty and honour: it is to fall into transgression’ (1: 34–5; 2:19, 33). By doing one’s caste duty here and now, therefore—in Arjuna’s case, as a warrior—whatever the consequences, one will acquire benefits through karma in one’s next life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a unique resolution to the conflict between morality and practicality. It avoids the Machiavellian move of denying the validity of moral norms. It implies a statist sense of duty to the public order comparable to what we find in Roman tradition (where Brutus allows the execution of his own son).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India - Kingship</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 05:59:37 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In ancient Indian theory, caste came first, kingship second. So this was sacred monarchy with a difference. Kingship, though sacred, was not the sole or supreme agency of the divine in society. It is true that &amp;lsquo;in the Vedic period the chief/king assumed identity with various gods during certain state rituals’; he could be regarded as a ‘deva’ with supernatural faculties. A good king could, as in Egypt, Mesopotamia, and China, have a beneficial effect on nature and the cosmos. But he was not identified with the supreme god Brahma, nor was he Brahma’s ‘Son or representative’. The fundamental role of sustaining the social order by ritual sacrifice and teaching the Vedas belonged to the brahmins. In the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; the relationship was expressed by saying that ‘a brahmin is the root of the tree of Justice; the sovereign prince is its stem and branches; the ministers are its leaves and blossoms; just government is its fruit’ (in Spellman 1964: 124). It is important to note, however, that in the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; the good king is generally portrayed as acting quite independently of brahmins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Egyptian and Mesopotamian traditions, the king could intervene in all aspects of social life—he was theoretically omnipotent. In India, kingship functioned alongside, and within, the system of castes. Varna received ‘most of the loyalty elsewhere felt towards king, nation and city’ (Finer 1997: 1211).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview&#34;&gt;Brahmanism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buddhism - Overview</title>
      <link>/posts/buddhism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:30 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/buddhism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two people key to its spread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;siddhartha-gautama&#34;&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born mid-sixth century BCE in the foothills of the Himalaya Mountains, in what is today southern Nepal, the son of a ruling kshatriya family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a family, left his family, meditated under a tree, achieved enlightenment, spent the rest of his life preaching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His ideas can be viewed as a reformist form of Brahmanism, designed to transfer responsibility from the priests to the individual, much as the sixteenth century German monk Martin Luther saw his ideas as a reformation of Christianity. Siddhartha accepted the concept of reincarnation and the role of karma as a means of influencing the movement of individual souls up and down the scale of life. Nirvana, the extinction of selfhood and reunion with the Great World Soul, is likened to a dreamless sleep, rather than the Christian concept of heavenly salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four noble truths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life is suffering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suffering is caused by desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end suffering is to end desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end desire is to avoid the extremes of a life of vulgar materialism and to follow the Middle Path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Middle Path: right knowledge, purpose, speech, conduct, occupation, effort, awareness, meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All human beings can aspire to Nirvana as a result of their behaviour in this life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siddharta Gautama died in 480 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ashoka&#34;&gt;Ashoka&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Converted to Buddhism in the third century BCE, and sent Buddhist missionaries throughout India, and ordered the erection of stone pillars with official edicts and Buddhist inscriptions to instruct people in the proper way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashoka died in 232 BCE, after which the Mauryan empire began to fragment into separate states - in 183 BCE, India reverted to disunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brahmanism - Overview</title>
      <link>/posts/brahmanism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/brahmanism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the Rig Vedas, when Brahma, the supreme god, destroyed himself to create the four classes of the society, the &lt;em&gt;brahmins&lt;/em&gt; - the priest class - were made from his head, the &lt;em&gt;kshatriyas&lt;/em&gt; - the warrior, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-kingship&#34;&gt;king&lt;/a&gt;, administrator class - were made from his arms, the &lt;em&gt;vaishyas&lt;/em&gt; - the merchants - were made from his thighs, and the &lt;em&gt;sudras&lt;/em&gt; - the labourers and servants - came from the feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brahmins, kshatriya, vaishyas, are &lt;em&gt;twice-born&lt;/em&gt; - undergoing a ceremony at puberty whereby they&amp;rsquo;re initiated into adulthood and Indian society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:39:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social hierarchy: classical texts specified &lt;em&gt;varna&lt;/em&gt;, a system of four classes in society; this was instantiated into the caste system, &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;, where people are born into a clan (&lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;) that specifies social and economic duty, and requirements for endogamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s thought that this class system was introduced by the Aryans, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-history/&#34;&gt;when they first arrived in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophies that emerged from this background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview/&#34;&gt;Brahmanism&lt;/a&gt;, which later developed into Hinduism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of which were underwritten by the concept of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; - the sum/worth of one&amp;rsquo;s actions in life that decide one&amp;rsquo;s fate in their next life, and in brahmanism, this is accumulated through carrying out &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; - ethics, duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/&#34;&gt;Dharma vs. Artha, Morality vs. Practicality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India History</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:02:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ca. 2600–1900 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harappan civilization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ca. 1500 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrival of the Aryans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ca. 560-480 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life of Gautama Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;326 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invasion of India by Alexander the Great&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;324 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauryan Dynasty founded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;324-301 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reign of Chandragupta Maurya&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;269-232 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reign of Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;183 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collapse of Mauryan Dynasty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the time of the Mauryans, Aryan buildings had been constructed of wood. With the rise of the empire, stone began to be used as artisans arrived in India seeking employment after the destruction of the Persian Empire by Alexander. Many of these stone carvers accepted the patronage of Emperor Ashoka, who used them to spread Buddhist ideas throughout the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>