<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>covenant on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/covenant/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (covenant)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:26 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/covenant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People</title>
      <link>/posts/israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:26 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gods-relationship-to-the-people&#34;&gt;God&amp;rsquo;s relationship to the people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental relationship was not between god and the king of Israel, but between god and the people of Israel. This was expressed as the covenant, originally between Yahweh and Abraham, including a pledge to his many descendants. I.e. it involved a &lt;em&gt;kinship group or race&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The individual recipients of the divine covenant are Abraham and Moses: great leaders, but long dead. The agreement with David is not called a ‘covenant’; it seems intended to add material about the state and royal dynasty, rather than as a recapitulation of what everyone knew to be the main body of the covenant, namely the Law. Rather, it was &lt;em&gt;the elders and the people who were the politically active agents at the time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main organizing force in Hebrew, and later Jewish, society was the law (ascribed to Yahweh) and the religious worship and ritual it prescribed; this Law had indeed been revealed to a historic leader, but he had transmitted it to the nation as a whole, not to a dynasty or institution. Hence divine legitimacy was bestowed not on the king but on the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, now positioned as the &lt;em&gt;primary political actor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;peoples-relationship-to-their-king&#34;&gt;People&amp;rsquo;s relationship to their king&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people were portrayed as playing a decisive part in the break-up of the kingdom of Israel and in the appointment of a rival king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was the people of the ten northern tribes of Israel that rejected Solomon&amp;rsquo;s designated heir, Rehoboam, and appointed Solomon&amp;rsquo;s younger son, Jeroboam (previously exiled by his father) as their king when they seceded from Judah.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘The men of Israel’ then ‘called [Jeroboam] to the assembly and made him king over the whole of Israel’. This was how Israel seceded from Judah, and from ‘the house of David’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people as compared to the king:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neither represent Yahweh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In matters of religious status and observances, the king was on a level with the people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The king could sometimes act as agent of the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; in a symbolic sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The king could be subjected to criticism for religious irregularities, or for failing to live up to the high standards of justice expected by legal and prophetic traditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>