<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>persian empire on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/persian-empire/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (persian empire)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:12:56 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/persian-empire/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel History</title>
      <link>/posts/israel-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:12:56 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/israel-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1200 - 1000 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Israelites emerge as a distinct group of people, possibly organized in tribes or a league of tribes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kingship - first kings: Saul, then David, then Solomon, who built the temple of Jerusalem. After the death of Solomon, tensions between northern and southern tribes in Israel lead to the establishment of two separate kingdoms—the kingdom of Israel, composed of the ten northern tribes, with its capital eventually at Samaria, and the kingdom of Judah, composed of two southern tribes, with its capital at Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;721-722 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assyrians overrun the kingdom of Israel, deporting the ten tribes to the rest of the Assyrian Empire - lost forever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;586 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaldeans defeats Assyria, conquers the kingdom of Judah, destroys Jerusalem. Upper-class people from Jerusalem are deported to Babylon - Psalm 137 is their lament: &lt;a href=&#34;../babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/&#34;&gt;Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;539 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Babylon falls to Persian empire. The Persians destroy the Chaldean kingdom and allow the people of Judah to return to Jerusalem and rebuild their city and Temple. The revived kingdom of Judah remains under Persian control until the conquests of Alexander the Great in the fourth century B.C.E.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>