<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>warring states period on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/warring-states-period/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (warring states period)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:29:50 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/warring-states-period/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hundred Schools of Thought</title>
      <link>/posts/hundred-schools-of-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:29:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/hundred-schools-of-thought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Main themes of Chinese political thought: state and monarchy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;state&#34;&gt;State&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature of scholar bureaucrats: 1. as political advisors, working in public service with a rank in the state hierarchy, they had a voice in the formation of the state; 2. as &lt;em&gt;itinerant&lt;/em&gt; political advisors, which gave them leverage and contributed to their intellectual independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no other culture would the history of thought and the history of the state be so closely intertwined. Ethical and philosophical reflection developed in response to the increasingly problematic political situation. This was the period of ‘a hundred schools’. China produced a greater variety of political ideas than any other monarchical agrarian civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;monarchy&#34;&gt;Monarchy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All Chinese theories emphasized the need for a single locus of authority, a quasi-absolute monarch, to resolve the problem of human discord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-qin-dynasty-inaugurated&#34;&gt;What Qin dynasty inaugurated&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than two millennia this imperial government seemed to have a staying-power and a power of self-renewal which one finds in religions—but less often in states—in other parts of the world. In ancient China [&amp;hellip;] ‘political thought’ had a somewhat different function from the equivalent genre elsewhere. It brought together what we in the West divide into the sacred and the secular. Religions such as Hinduism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam were similarly based on sacred texts. But these supported a system of belief and practice rather than a system of government. China was the only text-based state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;influential-belief-systems&#34;&gt;Influential belief systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-china-history/&#34;&gt;Ancient China History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient China History</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-china-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:09:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-china-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;?-ca. 1570 BCE: Xia Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning of Chinese civilization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1570-1045 BCE: Shang Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mastery of bronze casting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning of writing system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1045-221 BCE: Zhou Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of the Mandate of Heaven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mid sixth century BCE: introduction of iron -&amp;gt; development of iron plowshares, permitting deep plowing for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cultivation of wet rice becomes one of the prime sources of food in China, replacing other grain crops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advances in agriculture -&amp;gt; population rose as high as 20 million -&amp;gt; growth of commerce and manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the development of trade and manufacturing, China begins to move toward a money economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;551-479 BCE: Life of &lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
403-221 BCE:&lt;a href=&#34;../hundred-schools-of-thought/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hundred schools of thought&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;; warring states period&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
370-290 BCE: Life of Mengzi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;246 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Qin Shi Huang ascends to the throne of Qin at the age of 13&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;221-206 BCE: Qin Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standardization of weights, measures, monetary system, and written forms of Chinese characters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of mounted archers on a Great Wall to shoot down Xiongnu horseback warriors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establishment of eunuch system possibly to restrict influence of male courtiers for princesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;202 BCE: Han Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../han-confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Han Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;165 BCE: first known civil service examination for positions in the bureaucracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paper was invented under the Han, and the development of the rudder and fore-and-aft rigging permitted ships to sail into the wind for the first time. Thus equipped, Chinese merchants ships carrying heavy cargoes could sail throughout the islands of Southeast Asia and into the Indian Ocean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning of Silk Road (2nd century BCE - 18th century CE)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../qin-shi-huang-and-immortality/&#34;&gt;Qin Shi Huang and immortality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>