<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>literature on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/categories/literature/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (literature)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 14:39:36 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/categories/literature/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lament for Ur</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-lament-for-ur/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 14:39:36 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-lament-for-ur/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some extracts from the Lament for Ur, in which the goddess of Ur, Ningal, tells how she pleaded with the divine assembly, but to no avail, and the consequent destruction of Ur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then verily, to the assembly,&lt;br&gt;
where the crowd had not yet risen,&lt;br&gt;
while the Anunnaki, binding themselves&lt;br&gt;
(to uphold the decision), were still seated,&lt;br&gt;
I dragged my feet and I stretched out my arms,&lt;br&gt;
truly I shed my tears in front of An.&lt;br&gt;
Truly I myself mourned in front of Enlil:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;May my city not be destroyed!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
I said indeed to them.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;May Ur not be destroyed!&amp;rdquo; I said indeed to them.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;And may its people not be killed!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
I said indeed to them.&lt;br&gt;
But An never bent towards those words,&lt;br&gt;
and Enlil never with an, &amp;ldquo;It is pleasing, so be it!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
did soothe my heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Behold,) they gave instruction&lt;br&gt;
that the city be destroyed,&lt;br&gt;
(behold,) they gave instruction&lt;br&gt;
that Ur be destroyed,&lt;br&gt;
and as its destiny decreed&lt;br&gt;
that its inhabitants be killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city is doomed, and the execution of the terrible decree is left to Enlil. Stating in plain terms what we know happened we could say that wild mountaineers from the East - Elam and the Sua people - invaded Sumer, besieged Ur, and, when eventually the inhabitants surrendered the city, sacked and burned it mercilessly. But plain terms would be entirely inadequate to convey what the Sumerians knew took place. In a cosmic sense it was Enlil&amp;rsquo;s own destructive essence expressed in his element the storm that destroyed Ur. The wild hordes from the mountains were but incidental form in which that essence clothed itself, the reality was Enlil&amp;rsquo;s storm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enlil called the storm.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Winds of abundance he took from the land.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good winds he took away from Sumer.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Deputed evil winds.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Entrusted them to Kingaluda, tender of storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He called the storm that annihilates the land.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
He called disastrous winds.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Enlil - choosing Gibil as his helper -&lt;br&gt;
called the (great) hurricane of heaven.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
The (blinding) hurricane howling across the skies -&lt;br&gt;
the people mourn -&lt;br&gt;
the storm that annihilates the land roaring over the earth -&lt;br&gt;
the people mourn -&lt;br&gt;
the tempest unsubduable like breaks through levees,&lt;br&gt;
beats down upon, devours the city&amp;rsquo;s ships,&lt;br&gt;
(all these) he gathered at the base of heaven.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Great) fires he lit that heralded the storm.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
And lit on either flank of furious winds&lt;br&gt;
the searing heat of desert.&lt;br&gt;
Like flaming heat of noon this fire scorched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this storm that destroys the city:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm ordered by Enlil in hate,&lt;br&gt;
the storm which wears away the country,&lt;br&gt;
covered Ur like a cloth,&lt;br&gt;
veiled it like a linen sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it clears away all is over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that day did the storm leave the city;&lt;br&gt;
that city was a ruin.&lt;br&gt;
O father Nanna, that town was left a ruin.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
On that day did the storm leave the country.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Its people(&amp;lsquo;s corpses), not potsherds,&lt;br&gt;
littered the approaches.&lt;br&gt;
The walls were gaping;&lt;br&gt;
the high gates, the roads,&lt;br&gt;
were piled with dead.&lt;br&gt;
In the wide streets,&lt;br&gt;
where feasting crowds (once) gathered&lt;br&gt;
jumbled they lay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all the streets and roadways bodies lay.&lt;br&gt;
In open fields that used to fill with dancers,&lt;br&gt;
the people lay in heaps.&lt;br&gt;
The country&amp;rsquo;s blood now filled its holes,&lt;br&gt;
like metal in a mold;&lt;br&gt;
bodies dissolved - like butter left in the sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;] In reality, then, justice - that is to say, human justice - quails before the absolute authority of the unanimous will of the gods; they are not to be challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descent of Innana</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-descent-of-innana/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 14:21:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-descent-of-innana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story begins with a whim, a sudden desire of Inanna for the netherworld, a desire that comes to rule her to the exclusion of everything else:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She set her heart from highest heaven&lt;br&gt;
on earth&amp;rsquo;s deepest ground,&lt;br&gt;
the goddess set her heart from highest heaven&lt;br&gt;
on earth&amp;rsquo;s deepest ground,&lt;br&gt;
Inanna set her heart from highest heaven&lt;br&gt;
on earth&amp;rsquo;s deepest ground,&lt;br&gt;
milady abandoned heaven, abandoned earth,&lt;br&gt;
went down to Hades,&lt;br&gt;
Inanna abandoned heaven, abandoned earth,&lt;br&gt;
went down to Hades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when she comes up to find a substitute for her death, she sees her husband enjoying himself. And so she gives the deputies of death their head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She looked at him, it was a look of death,&lt;br&gt;
spoke to them, it was a word of wrath&lt;br&gt;
cried out to them, it was the cry of &amp;ldquo;guilty!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Take this one along!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
Holy Inanna gave the shepherd Dumuzi into their hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sumerian Wedding Texts</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-wedding-texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 13:40:01 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-wedding-texts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-the-cultivators-wedding-text&#34;&gt;1. The cultivators&amp;rsquo; wedding text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The sequence of the nuptial drama is thus clear, but a great deal of the meaning of the text remains dark and unexplained. To understand this we must understand what the powers stand for.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bride, Inanna, represents the numen of the communal storehouse for dates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bridegroom, Dumuzi, represents what is to be stored in the storehouse - the power behind the yearly burgeoning of the palm and its producing its yield of dates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, for example, is the odd &amp;ldquo;gem-revealing heap&amp;rdquo;?&lt;br&gt;
Why do Inanna&amp;rsquo;s wedding ornaments come from it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That a heap of fresh dates should furnish the ornaments for Inanna is logical since freshly harvested dates are the pride and adornment of the bare shelves of a storehouse for dates. The date clusters that are to adorn the shelves of the storehouse become ritually experienced as traditional feminine adornments and jewelry such as would be suitable for decking out a human bride, and the heap from thich they are taken comes close to becoming ajewel shrine of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is Dumuzi to be taken back to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That these two powers are wed means that the power for fertility and yield has been captured by the numen of the storehouse - and so by the community - and has become its trusty provider for all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dumuzi is safely in the storehouse, and the community revels in abundant food and drink, release from anxiety and fear of starvation, blissfully secure from want. Inanna expresses the communal feeling precisely: not love or the raptures of passion mark her wedding night, but a gently glowing sense of inner and outer bliss in trust and security:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not only is it sweet to sleep hand in hand with him,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sweetest of sweet is too the loveliness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;of joining heart to heart with him.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-later-developments-of-the-cultivators-wedding-text&#34;&gt;2. Later developments of the cultivators&amp;rsquo; wedding text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of blessings expected increases. Now it ranges from  the yields of farmers and shepherds to the take of fishermen and fowlers, from the wildlife in woods and marshes to the produce of vineyards and gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contrasts with the first cultic wedding text, the Uruk Text. There the god, Dumuzi-Amaushumgalanna, was the power in the fertility and yield of the date palm only, and the underlying ritual was a date harvest ritual and nothing else. This concentration on a single major economy is, we should judge, an original feature, but as the cities drew a variety of economies into their orbit - Uruk, for instance, seems to have united several settlements of date growers, oxherders, and shepherds - the purview of the cult broadened so as to make its god stand for a general fertility and yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a broadening is already suggested on the Uruk Vase of the outgoing fourth millennium where the bridal gifts brought by the god include not only dates but ears of grain and sheep heavy with wool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Different portrayals of this economic diversification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumuzi is a shepherd; the farmer, the fishermen, and the fowler are wedding attendants, bringing gifts of their product to supplement what the shepherd provides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumuzi is both a shepherd and farmer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-the-herders-wedding-text&#34;&gt;3. The herders&amp;rsquo; wedding text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the song Inanna, glorying in her young body, which has just attained puberty, sings the praises of her pubic triangle with its as yet sparse growth of hairs, comparing it first to a metal enchasement with decorative studs sticking out like linchpins in a cartwheel, then to a ceremonial barge called the &amp;ldquo;Barge of Heaven&amp;rdquo; (the recent hairs she sees as mooring ropes holding the barge), and the image leads over into that of the cosmic barge of heaven, the crescent of the new moon. Next her triangle has become a virginal plot in the desert, not yet cultivated, then again a stubble field on which ducks have been put out to be fattened, black hairs dotting it like black ducks against light dun soil, then it is a high-lying field, hillock land, piled up with levees, well watered in readiness for ploughing - she has just bathed in water - and then moist lowlands similarly readied. Since a woman, though she may own fields, cannot herself plough them but must seek a ploughman to do it for her, the song ends with the question of who he should be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;My enchased parts so nailed down&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;as (with) linchpins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;attached to a big cart,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(my crescent-shaped) &amp;ldquo;Barge of Heaven,&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;so (well) belayed,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;full of loveliness, like the new moon,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my untilled plot,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;left so fallow in the desert,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my duck field so studded with ducks,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my hillock land, so (well) watered,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my parts, piled up with levees,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(well) watered&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I, being (but) a maiden,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;who will be their ploughman?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My parts, (well) watered lowlands,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I, being (but) a lady,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;who will put (plough) oxen to them?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the elegist responds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Young lady, may the king plough them for you!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;May the king, Dumuzi, plough them for you!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is obviously the right answer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;The man of my heart! The ploughman is the man of my heart!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Herder Wedding Text&amp;rdquo; ends on much the same note as the other wedding texts, with delight in great abundances of food. Yet, there is one subtle difference. The riches here garnered by Inanna - milk and milk products - are short-term only. They will not, like the more durable riches of the date harvest, last through an approaching dry season and free the community from want until the next season. The sense of having reached security which informs the wedding texts of Amaushumgalanna can have little relevance in the herder&amp;rsquo;s world with its swiftly passing blessings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That world has, rather, its own set of relevant experiences. In spring the desert fills with green, the herds gambol in the pastures and mate, and from that mating flows the herder&amp;rsquo;s prosperity; increase of flocks and herds, newborn lambs, kids, and calves, plentiful milk from the full udders of the mother animals. In the herder&amp;rsquo;s view the emphasis of the sacred marriage is therefore on its mating aspect. He sees it as a divine engendering which brings into being spring&amp;rsquo;s glorious burst, the sacred cosmic sexual act in which all nature is fertilized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This emphasis comes through clearly in Inanna&amp;rsquo;s frank praise of her private parts with its central image of the field ready for the fertilizing seed plough - an image, incidentally, which still does not take us outside the herder&amp;rsquo;s world since the plough oxen were provided by the cowherders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the orchardman&amp;rsquo;s and the herder&amp;rsquo;s rite of the sacred marriage differ fundamentally. The first is a harvest rite binding the date palm&amp;rsquo;s power for fertility and yield to the numen of the storehouse in bonds of marriage and mutual love. The other is a fertility rite uniting - by incarnating them in human actors - the divine powers for fertility and new life in a generative sexual embrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deadly Diseases</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-deadly-diseases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 13:37:07 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-deadly-diseases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The shivers and chills (of death)
that fritter the sum of things,
spawn of the god of heaven,
spawned on an evil spirit,
the death warrants, beloved sons of the storm god,
born of the queen of the netherworld,
who were torn out of heaven and hurled from the earth as castoffs, are creatures of hell, all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up above they roar, down below they cheep,
they are the bitter venom of the gods,
they are the great storms let loose from heaven,
they are the owl (of ill omen) that hoots in the town,
spawn spawned by the god of heaven, sons born by earth
are they.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over high roofs, over broad roofs like a floodwave
they surge,
from house to house they climb over,
Doors do not hold them, locks do not restrain them,
through the doors they glide like snakes,
through the hinge boxes they blow like wind.
From the man&amp;rsquo;s embrace they lead off the wife,
from the man&amp;rsquo;s knee they make the child get up,
and the youth they fetch out of the house of his in-laws,
they are the numbness, the daze,
that tread on the heels of man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;Most Ancient Verse&lt;/em&gt;. The University of Chicago Press, 1963.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>