<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>history on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/categories/history/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (history)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 10:53:42 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/categories/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tyranny in Ancient Greece</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/tyranny-in-ancient-greece/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 10:53:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/tyranny-in-ancient-greece/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In many poleis, the circle of the aristocratic elite tightened further as smaller and smaller groups came to dominate higher offices. One option for aristocrats left outside of their own culture, looking in was to form an alliance with the rising class of hoplites, who had complaints of their own about exclusion from poitical power. And occasionally, a single aristocrat with the backing othe hoplites would succeed in setting up an alternative form of government, a &lt;em&gt;tyranny&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tyranny: its meaning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The word &lt;em&gt;tyrannos&lt;/em&gt; had been borrowed from the Lydians: it signified someone who ruled outside the traditional framework of the polis. A tyrant was not necessarily an abusive ruler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and implications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tyranny often led the way to wider political enfranchisement: a would-be tyrant who had sought the support of the hoplite class would have to appease that class by extending further rights of poitical participation, while all the time striving to keep the reins of power in his own hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tyrannies rarely lasted for more than two generations and could drive transition from aristocracy to a more broadly participatory form of government: democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sea Peoples Sweep Across the Eastern Mediterranean</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/the-sea-peoples-sweep-across-the-eastern-mediterranean/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 15:18:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/the-sea-peoples-sweep-across-the-eastern-mediterranean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The invading/displaced Sea Peoples from the Aegean swept across the Eastern Mediterranean c. 1200 BCE. The Hittite Empire collapsed, Ugarit was permanently destroyed, and Egypt went into decline, despite the victory of Ramses III. Fortunately, the Phoenician cities survived (one theory is that they allied themselves with the Sea Peoples). Ill-fated, the Mycenaean civilization also fell and, thus, Greece entered its “Dark Age”. Western culture was devastated and now largely isolated from the cosmopolitan Near East. Creating a vast, mercantile network—as well as filling the Aegean vacuum—was Phoenicia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Scott, John C. (2018) &amp;ldquo;The Phoenicians and the Formation of the Western World,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Comparative Civilizations Review&lt;/em&gt;: Vol. 78 : No. 78 , Article 4.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient Greece History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-greece-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 08:16:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-greece-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1950-1450 BCE: Height of Minoan civilization&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1600 BCE: Thera (modern day Santorini) erupts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1200 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../the-sea-peoples-sweep-across-the-eastern-mediterranean/&#34;&gt;The Sea Peoples sweep across the Eastern Mediterranean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1000 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greeks were starting to copy Phoenician designs for merchant vessels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flourishing of Greek commerce, expansion of population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;900 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rise of the polis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;800-500 BCE: Archaic Greece&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I believe that the earth is very large and that we who dwell between the pillars of Hercules and the river Phasis live in a small part of it about the sea, like ants or frogs about a pond, and that many other people live in many other such regions.” - Socrates. (Plato, Phaedo 109a,b)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;800 BCE: Greeks adopt Phoenician alphabet, replacing the Mycenean Linear B&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;776 BCE: First Olympic Games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;750 BCE: Colonization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;725-625 BCE: Hoplite tactics become standard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;600 BCE: Militarization of Sparta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;600-500 BCE: Emergence of Milesian School&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;594 BCE: Solon&amp;rsquo;s reforms in Athens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;546 BCE: Cyrus of Persia conquers Lydia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;510 BCE: Overthrow of Peisistratid tyrants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;500-450 BCE: The Persian Empire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;499-494 BCE: Ionian Revolt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;490 BCE: Battle of Marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;480 BCE: Battle of Thermopylae and Salamis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;479 BCE: Battle of Plataea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;478 BCE: Formation of Delian League&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;450-350 BCE: Infighting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;431-404 BCE: Peloponnesian War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;399 BCE: Death of Socrates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;336-bce-alexander-the-great-becomes-king&#34;&gt;336 BCE: Alexander the Great becomes King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Athenian Democracy</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/athenian-democracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:22:13 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/athenian-democracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to depending on the labor and fertility of women, Athenians were as reliant on slaves as Spartans were on helots. Without slavery, none of the Athenian accomplishments in politics, thought, or art would have been possible. The Athenian ideal of dividing and rotating governmental duties among all free men depended on slaves who worked in fields, businesses, and homes while free men engaged in politics. In fact, the Athenian democratic system began to function fully only with the expansion of Athenian mining and commerce around 500 B.C.E., which enabled the Athenians to buy slaves in larger numbers. Freedom and slavery were thus an inescapable contradiction of this democracy—much as they would be many centuries later in the United States, prior to the Civil War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more ways than one, Athenian freedom rested on the servitude of others. Slaves performed much of the labor at home, while Athens’ allies in the Delian League provided the resources that supported Athenian greatness. Without the surplus wealth flowing into Athens from the league, none of the projects Pericles undertook—pay for political participation, massive building projects, the patronage of Athenian drama—would have been possible. These projects kept Athens rich, its democracy vibrant, and Pericles in power. But ultimately, Athens’ foreign policy and imperial ambitions undermined these achievements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Athenian Political Background</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/athenian-political-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:22:03 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/athenian-political-background/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;consolidation-of-power-through-the-archaic-period&#34;&gt;Consolidation of power through the Archaic Period&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristocratic monopolization of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;elected offices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the city council, &lt;em&gt;Areopagus&lt;/em&gt;, which was composed of former office holders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;archonship&#34;&gt;Archonship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the seventh century BCE, executive authority in Athens lay entirely with the nine &lt;em&gt;archons&lt;/em&gt; presiding over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a high court with influence over hearing of cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appointed by the Areopagus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one year term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lifetime membership in the Areopagus after&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outcome of inequality: a significant proportion of the population fell into slavery through debt, while struggles among aristocratic families destabilized the government and fomented cycles of revenge killings. This situation eventually inspired the Athenians&amp;rsquo; first attempt to promulgate a set of written laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;establishing-democracy&#34;&gt;Establishing democracy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drakon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peisistratos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spartan-sponsored oligarchy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleisthenes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drakon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Also known as Draco, Drako. The first recorded legislator of Athens, replacing the prevailing system of oral law and blood feud with the first written constitution of Athens in 621 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His laws were harsh, hence &amp;ldquo;draconian&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
A poet elected in 594 BCE as the sole archon for a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solon’s legendary political and economic reforms laid the foundations for the later development of Athenian democracy. He forbade the practice of debt slavery and set up a fund to buy back Athenian slaves who had been sold abroad. He encouraged the cultivation of olives and grapes, thus spurring cash-crop farming and urban industries such as oil and wine production, and the manufacture of pottery storage jars and decorative drinking cups. He also broadened rights of political participation and set up courts in which a range of citizens served as jurors and to which any Athenian might appeal. He based eligibility for political office on property qualifications, thus making it possible for someone not born into the aristocracy to gain access to power. Moreover, he convened an Athenian assembly, the &lt;em&gt;ekklesia&lt;/em&gt; and gave it the right to elect archons. Now all free-born Athenian men over the age of eighteen could participate in government. Even those who were not eligible for citizenship were able to see the workings of government for themselves, since the assembled citizens met on the slopes of the Pnyx, a hill visible from the central marketplace and overlooked by the sacred precincts of the Acropolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solon’s reforms were not immediately accepted. The aristocracy thought them too radical; the people of the demos, not radical enough. In the resulting generation of turmoil&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peisistratos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
546 BCE: An aristocrat named Peisistratos establishes himself as tyrant (see: &lt;a href=&#34;../tyranny-in-ancient-greece/&#34;&gt;Tyranny in Ancient Greece&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat ironically, Peisistratos proceeds to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;institute Solon&amp;rsquo;s reforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;launch a massive campaign of public works projects, including the collection and condification of Homer&amp;rsquo;s epics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;crush dissent mercilessly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ultimately, strengthen the political role of the demos and so remain a popular ruler until his death.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His sons were less able to control the various factions that threatened their rule; one was assassinated and the other was ousted with the help of the Spartans in 510 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;spartan-sponsored-oligarchy&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spartan-sponsored oligarchy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleisthenes&lt;/strong&gt;
Two generations of increasing access to power had left the Athenian demos with a taste for self-government, and a group of commoners rallied behind Cleisthenes, an aristocrat who championed the cause of the demos. Once voted in as archon in 508/7 BCE, Cleisthenes took steps to limit aristocratic power by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reorganizing the Athenian population into ten voting districts, hence suppressing traditional loyalties tied to certain aristocratic families&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strengthening Athenian assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extending democracy to the local level throughout Attica&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;introducing ostracism - whereby Athenians could decide each year whether they wanted to banish someone for a decade and, if so, whom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleisthenes hoped that with this, the demos could 1. prevent the return of a tyrant 2. quell factional strife if civil war seemed imminent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;by-500-bce&#34;&gt;By 500 BCE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The political struggles of the sixth century had given Athens a far more populist character than any other Greek polis and had strengthened its institutions of government. In the meantime, Athens had become the principal exporter of olive oil, wine, and pottery in the Greek world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;persian-wars&#34;&gt;Persian Wars&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Background: in the decades before the Persian Wars, political reforms in Athens had continued to encourage further experiments in democracy, including the practice of selecting major officeholders by lot. Only one key position was now filled by traditional voting: the office of &lt;em&gt;strategos&lt;/em&gt;, or general. And because a man could be elected stratgos year after year, this office became the career goal of Athens&amp;rsquo;s most ambitious figures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Themistocles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When the Athenians discovered a rich vein of silver ore in the Attic countryside, Themistocles persuaded them not to divide the windfall among themselves (the customary practice) but to finance a fleet of 200 triremes - state-of-the-art warships - thereby transforming Athens into the preeminent naval power of the Greek World&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cimon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;hellip;just in time to confront a new Persian onslaught, as Cimon led the Delian league to victories in 470s and 460s BCE. But Cimon also used the league to punish poleis who tried to opt out of membership, suppressing revolts by force of arms and turning the league into an instrument of Athenian policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 462-461 BCE, Cimon was ostracised by his rival&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pericles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;hellip;an aristocrat from one of Athens&amp;rsquo;s richest families, who rose to strategos on the enfranchisement of the thetes, the lowest class of free men and the rowers of the triremes, as his political platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He oversaw:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a foreign policy oriented away from cooperation with Sparta&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reforms that gave every citizen the right to propose and amend legislation, not just to vote yes or no in the citizen assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an average day&amp;rsquo;s wage for attendance in the assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and through the latter measures, thetes and other free men of modest means becoming a dominant force in politics, and loyal to the man who made that dominance possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the ambitions of Pericles, this populist program glorified Athens through an ambitious scheme of public building and lavish festivals honoring the gods, especially Athena. Personally, too, Pericles was a generous patron of the arts and sciences, attracting the greatest minds and talents of the day to Athens. His popularity, combined with his charisma and his promotion of the Athenians’ sense of superiority, ensured his reelection as strategos for the next three decades. During these years Athens flourished, but it also alienated much of the Greek world by its arrogance and aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transnational Diplomacy and Trade in 14th Century BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 04:36:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Region: West Asia and Mediterranean&lt;br&gt;
Time: 14th century BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This Late Bronze Age was an age of superpowers. The great pharaohs of the Eighteenth Dynasty had transformed Egypt into a conquering state, and the Hittites had created an empire out of the disparate city-states and kingdoms of Anatolia. The Assyrians controlled Near Eastern trade, and the Kassite kingdom of Babylonia remained a significant force in economic and military relationships. In addition to these imperial entities, numerous smaller states also flourished and extended their influence westward into the Mediterranean. Holding it all together was a network of trade routes that created an interdependent Afro-Eurasian world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational diplomacy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../amarna-letter-ea4/&#34;&gt;letters between rulers/elites&lt;/a&gt;, found in Akhenaten&amp;rsquo;s abandoned capital of Akhetaten (modern el-Amarna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marriage contracts between rulers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other lavish gifts (greeting gifts for festivals and such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptians delighted in Canaanite glass, Greeks prized Egyptian amulets, and the merchants of Syria admired Greek pottery and wool.
This was the background for the development of the abjad (the consonant-only family of alphabet later giving rise to the Phoenician alphabet). Ugarit, on the coast of modern-day Syria, developed the Ugaritic alphabet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confucianism and Population Density</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/confucianism-population-density/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 02:43:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/confucianism-population-density/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Li, in Confucianism, is a formalization of the philosophy behind the clearly sanctioned rules and behaviour that underpin Asian societies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High yields have always supported large populations in monsoon Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The states and empires of monsoon Asia were built consistently on their common peasant base of intensive, high-yield agriculture, which provided the great bulk of revenues, the manpower for armies, and the highly structured social order. [&amp;hellip;] The village worlds were largely self-governing and self-regulating, thanks to the family system, the kin network, and the basic social institutions common to the area as a whole, but they formed the essential foundation for the building and maintenance of empires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Murphey, Rhoads. &lt;em&gt;A History of Asia&lt;/em&gt;. Routledge, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Han Confucianism</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/han-confucianism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:55:49 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/han-confucianism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Background: unification and centralization by Qin provided a milieu in which the gentlemanly culture of Confucianism could flourish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Confucianism was thus a conflation of earlier Confucianism, mystical cosmology, and authoritarian statism (CHC i. 107, 652). The Zhou notion of monarchy had been transformed, but the nature and extent of the change was not apparent in the language used. The ‘institutional framework’ was and remained a ‘legalist autocracy’ (Wang and Chang 1986: 12). But the state could now afford to be benevolent. Chinese historians have called it ‘outside Confucian, inside legalist’ (Zhengyuan Fu 1996: 8). As Bodde put it, ‘it is the Legalist/Confucian symbiosis evolved during the Han, with administrative controls at the top merging into self-administered behavioural standards below, that gave to the Chinese state the necessary combination of firmness and flexibility that enabled it to survive’ (CHC i. 90).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>China - Government by Non-Intervention</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;legalism1-and-daoism2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principal text: Guanzi (管子)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By being ‘empty and still’, the emperor is supposed to be able to identify the ‘regulatory principles’ of the Dao which operate in both the natural and the human worlds. The &lt;em&gt;Guanzi&lt;/em&gt; insisted that ‘statutes, regulations, and measures be modeled on the Dao’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the right laws, in harmony with the cosmic principles, are in place, then the ruler just has to leave everyone to follow them. The actual business of government is in the hands of the chief minister and bureaucracy. This may be compared to Max Weber&amp;rsquo;s notion of a rule-bound bureaucracy (which he saw as characteristic of a modern state) under a charismatic head. It is bureaucrats who govern while the monarch maintains a ‘mystical link to the cosmic flow’: ‘administration is not his business’ (Lüshi Chunqiu, in ST 237). The ruler does not need to make personal decisions as such. As Shen Bu-Hai first put it, ‘he does not act, yet as a result of his non-action the world brings itself to a state of complete order’ (in Creel 1974: 64).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;entrapped-sovereign&#34;&gt;Entrapped Sovereign&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Fei shared his predecessors’ view of the ruler as the pivot of sociopolitical order, the sole guarantor of stability and prosperity of his subjects; yet he was also bitterly aware of the ruler’s inadequacy. The very fact that the monarch—unlike his officials—owes his position to pedigree alone means that this position will more often than not be occupied by a mediocrity. Multiple historical examples scattered throughout &lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; unequivocally demonstrate how devastating the ruler’s ineptitude can be. The intrinsic contradiction between an &lt;em&gt;institutionally infallible and humanly erring sovereign&lt;/em&gt; is the major source of tension in the Han Feizi (Pines 2013b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations: remain empty and tranquil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruler does not reveal his desires; should he do so, the minister will carve and embellish them. He does not reveal his views; should he do so, the minister will use them to present his different [opinion]. … The way of the enlightened sovereign is to let the knowledgeable completely exhaust their contemplations—then the ruler relies on them to decide on matters and is not depleted of knowledge; to let the worthy utilize their talents—then the ruler relies on them, assigns tasks, and is not depleted of abilities. When there is success, the ruler possesses a worthy [name]; when there is failure, the minister bears the responsibility. (&lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; 5: 27)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the paradox of the entrapped sovereign, who enjoys God-like omnipotence, but who is required to refrain from any activism in order to preserve this omnipotence - a manifestation of the intrinsic contradiction of the authoritarian system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Pines, Yuri, &amp;ldquo;Legalism in Chinese Philosophy&amp;rdquo;, The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Winter 2018 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), URL = &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&#34;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daoism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/daoism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 07:07:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/daoism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Laozi: Confucius&amp;rsquo;s contemporary. Daoism is authored in 道德经.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laozi proposed a return to primitive simplicity, withdrawal from the world, spontaneity. They thought that society had become overdeveloped, overheated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;The more prohibitions and rules, the poorer the people become&amp;hellip; The more elaborate the laws, the more they commit crimes&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corruption and oppression were the inevitable results of civilization and were brought about precisely by those whom others idealized—rulers and sages. In this view, the state is part of the problem, part of humanity’s misguided attempt to control the world. Solutions to human problems are to be sought only in the individual mind. This was the counter-culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;monarchy&#34;&gt;Monarchy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Daoists thought that the sage-ruler is himself &amp;lsquo;the unmoving director of the world&amp;rsquo;: his beneficence consists in going with the flow of events, like water flowing downhill; Laozi spoke of a sage-ruler perfectly in tune with Heaven and Earth, and with &amp;lsquo;the hearts and minds of the people&amp;rsquo;. &amp;lsquo;When he acts, he takes no credit&amp;rsquo;, for &amp;lsquo;the people say &amp;ldquo;we did it ourselves&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../china-government-by-non-intervention/&#34;&gt;China - Government by Non-Intervention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legalism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/legalism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 07:06:58 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/legalism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A ruler undertakes policies which, even though ‘people do not have the sense to rejoice in them’, are for their long-term benefit (Han Feizi, Basic Writings, 128–9); he ‘does not indulge the people’s desires, he simply looks ahead for what will benefit them’. The ruler may have to enforce his measures ‘against the will of the people’. The goals of the state—prosperity, stability, and expansion—were the only ones which would make life tolerable for the majority of people, and they were ones which people would choose if they could see sufficiently far ahead. This was their justification for compulsory labour, taxation, military service, and severe punishments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the reasoning behind the policy, advocated by Shang Yang and
others, and first implemented in the state of Qin, of making punishments
exceptionally severe but predictable. With what would nowadays appear
breathtaking honesty, they advocated rule by fear as the most efficient way of securing the greatest good of the greatest number (Han Feizi, Basic Writings, 104). Only when light offences are ‘regarded as serious’ do ‘serious ones have no chance of coming’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;War and killing are permissible so long as the aim is to abolish them. This means achieving what people want by means they do not want (Book of Lord Shang, 230, 285). It is only by going against the wishes of the people that you make them happy. ‘What I call punishment is the basis of righteousness, but what the world calls righteousness is the way of violence’ (Han Feizi, in Wang and Chang 1986: 46). In other words, they were implying that the outcome desired by Confucius could only be achieved by means he refused to contemplate. It simply could not be achieved by persuasion and example (Book of Lord Shang, 325). The true lesson of history was that a great king ‘seized the world by force, but held it by righteousness’—an almost prophetic statement when one looks at the first two dynasties of the Chinese empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../china-government-by-non-intervention/&#34;&gt;China - Government by Non-Intervention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Confucianism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/confucianism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 07:06:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/confucianism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Confucius: 551 - 479 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;li-and-ren&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Li&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ren&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Li&lt;/em&gt;: ritual, custom, decorum, propriety, ethics - a concept extended from a code of conduct and traditional conventions of social intercourse to embrace a &amp;ldquo;broad range of political activities, such as personnel policy, [and] proper handling of rewards and punishments&amp;rdquo;, so that it came to comprise the &amp;ldquo;entire way of governing&amp;rdquo;. Interpretation of the ethical and societal norms of &lt;em&gt;li&lt;/em&gt; was the focus of Confucian thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ren&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lsquo;to overcome the self and turn to &lt;em&gt;li&lt;/em&gt;. The inner rationale that motivates people to observe &lt;em&gt;li&lt;/em&gt;. The humaneness that legitimizes political order (as interpreted by Mengzi, Confucius&amp;rsquo;s disciple). Confucius insisted that humaneness was the fundamental norm not only ofhuman conduct, but of political conduct and civilized government. It laid down both the goal and the methods of politics; it stipulated a harmonious society in which the virtuous lead by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Confucius, government works best when the ruler is humane; the praxis was government by consensus - Heaven looking out from the little people, which enlightened paternalism is needed to lead, teach, and treat well. Persuasion is better than coercion. Confucius saw violence as the break- down of politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confucianism saw the state as a family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implementations&#34;&gt;Implementations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../han-confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Han Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India - Kingship</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 05:59:37 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In ancient Indian theory, caste came first, kingship second. So this was sacred monarchy with a difference. Kingship, though sacred, was not the sole or supreme agency of the divine in society. It is true that &amp;lsquo;in the Vedic period the chief/king assumed identity with various gods during certain state rituals’; he could be regarded as a ‘deva’ with supernatural faculties. A good king could, as in Egypt, Mesopotamia, and China, have a beneficial effect on nature and the cosmos. But he was not identified with the supreme god Brahma, nor was he Brahma’s ‘Son or representative’. The fundamental role of sustaining the social order by ritual sacrifice and teaching the Vedas belonged to the brahmins. In the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; the relationship was expressed by saying that ‘a brahmin is the root of the tree of Justice; the sovereign prince is its stem and branches; the ministers are its leaves and blossoms; just government is its fruit’ (in Spellman 1964: 124). It is important to note, however, that in the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; the good king is generally portrayed as acting quite independently of brahmins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Egyptian and Mesopotamian traditions, the king could intervene in all aspects of social life—he was theoretically omnipotent. In India, kingship functioned alongside, and within, the system of castes. Varna received ‘most of the loyalty elsewhere felt towards king, nation and city’ (Finer 1997: 1211).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview&#34;&gt;Brahmanism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:39:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social hierarchy: classical texts specified &lt;em&gt;varna&lt;/em&gt;, a system of four classes in society; this was instantiated into the caste system, &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;, where people are born into a clan (&lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;) that specifies social and economic duty, and requirements for endogamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s thought that this class system was introduced by the Aryans, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-history/&#34;&gt;when they first arrived in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophies that emerged from this background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview/&#34;&gt;Brahmanism&lt;/a&gt;, which later developed into Hinduism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of which were underwritten by the concept of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; - the sum/worth of one&amp;rsquo;s actions in life that decide one&amp;rsquo;s fate in their next life, and in brahmanism, this is accumulated through carrying out &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; - ethics, duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/&#34;&gt;Dharma vs. Artha, Morality vs. Practicality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hundred Schools of Thought</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/hundred-schools-of-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:29:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/hundred-schools-of-thought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Main themes of Chinese political thought: state and monarchy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;state&#34;&gt;State&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature of scholar bureaucrats: 1. as political advisors, working in public service with a rank in the state hierarchy, they had a voice in the formation of the state; 2. as &lt;em&gt;itinerant&lt;/em&gt; political advisors, which gave them leverage and contributed to their intellectual independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no other culture would the history of thought and the history of the state be so closely intertwined. Ethical and philosophical reflection developed in response to the increasingly problematic political situation. This was the period of ‘a hundred schools’. China produced a greater variety of political ideas than any other monarchical agrarian civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;monarchy&#34;&gt;Monarchy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All Chinese theories emphasized the need for a single locus of authority, a quasi-absolute monarch, to resolve the problem of human discord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-qin-dynasty-inaugurated&#34;&gt;What Qin dynasty inaugurated&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than two millennia this imperial government seemed to have a staying-power and a power of self-renewal which one finds in religions—but less often in states—in other parts of the world. In ancient China [&amp;hellip;] ‘political thought’ had a somewhat different function from the equivalent genre elsewhere. It brought together what we in the West divide into the sacred and the secular. Religions such as Hinduism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam were similarly based on sacred texts. But these supported a system of belief and practice rather than a system of government. China was the only text-based state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;influential-belief-systems&#34;&gt;Influential belief systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-china-history/&#34;&gt;Ancient China History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Beginning of the Silk Road</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/the-beginning-of-the-silk-road/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:54:24 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/the-beginning-of-the-silk-road/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;138 BCE:
The Han armies marched westward as far as the Caspian Sea, pacifying nomadic peoples and extending China&amp;rsquo;s boundary far into Central Asia, &lt;em&gt;originally to seek alliance to counter the common Xiongnu menace&lt;/em&gt;, but thereafter &lt;em&gt;Chinese commercial exchanges with people in Central Asia began to expand dramatically.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;effects&#34;&gt;Effects:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spread of Buddhism from South Asia to China in the first century CE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism - Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Qin Shi Huang and Immortality</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/qin-shi-huang-and-immortality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:45:46 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/qin-shi-huang-and-immortality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By ruthlessly gathering control over the empire into his own hands, Qin Shi Huangdi had hoped to establish a rule that, in the words of the contemporary historian Sima Qian, “would be enjoyed by his sons for ten thousand generations.” In fact, his centralizing zeal alienated many key groups. Landed aristocrats and Confucian intellectuals, as well as the common people, groaned under the censorship of thought and speech, harsh taxes, and forced labor projects. “He killed men,” recounted the historian, “as though he thought he could never finish, he punished men as though he were afraid he would never get around to them all, and the whole world revolted against him.” Shortly after the emperor died in 210 B.C.E., the dynasty quickly descended into factional rivalry, and four years later it was overthrown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient China History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-china-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:09:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-china-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;?-ca. 1570 BCE: Xia Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning of Chinese civilization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1570-1045 BCE: Shang Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../shang-china-developed-alone/&#34;&gt;Mastery of bronze casting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../shang-china-developed-alone/&#34;&gt;Beginning of writing system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1045-221 BCE: Zhou Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of the Mandate of Heaven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mid sixth century BCE: introduction of iron -&amp;gt; development of iron plowshares, permitting deep plowing for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cultivation of wet rice becomes one of the prime sources of food in China, replacing other grain crops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advances in agriculture -&amp;gt; population rose as high as 20 million -&amp;gt; growth of commerce and manufacturing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the development of trade and manufacturing, China begins to move toward a money economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;551-479 BCE: Life of &lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
403-221 BCE: &lt;a href=&#34;../hundred-schools-of-thought/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hundred schools of thought&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;;** warring states period**&lt;br&gt;
370-290 BCE: Life of Mengzi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;246 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Qin Shi Huang ascends to the throne of Qin at the age of 13&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;221-206 BCE: Qin Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standardization of weights, measures, monetary system, and written forms of Chinese characters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction of mounted archers on a Great Wall to shoot down Xiongnu horseback warriors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establishment of eunuch system possibly to restrict influence of male courtiers for princesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;202 BCE: Han Dynasty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../han-confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Han Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;165 BCE: first known civil service examination for positions in the bureaucracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paper was invented under the Han, and the development of the rudder and fore-and-aft rigging permitted ships to sail into the wind for the first time. Thus equipped, Chinese merchants ships carrying heavy cargoes could sail throughout the islands of Southeast Asia and into the Indian Ocean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beginning of Silk Road (2nd century BCE - 18th century CE)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../qin-shi-huang-and-immortality/&#34;&gt;Qin Shi Huang and immortality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:02:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ca. 2600–1900 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harappan civilization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ca. 1500 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrival of the Aryans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ca. 560-480 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life of Gautama Buddha&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;326 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invasion of India by Alexander the Great&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;324 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauryan Dynasty founded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;324-301 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reign of Chandragupta Maurya&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;269-232 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reign of Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;183 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collapse of Mauryan Dynasty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the time of the Mauryans, Aryan buildings had been constructed of wood. With the rise of the empire, stone began to be used as artisans arrived in India seeking employment after the destruction of the Persian Empire by Alexander. Many of these stone carvers accepted the patronage of Emperor Ashoka, who used them to spread Buddhist ideas throughout the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:35:05 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Features that have shaped Israelite political thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Untouchably high God - implications for egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Covenant - implications for political power of people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Exile - implications for human condition and suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:23:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By the rivers of Babylon, we sat and wept when we remembered Zion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There on the poplars we hung our harps,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For there our captors asked us for songs, our tormentors demanded songs of joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;They said, &amp;ldquo;Sing us one of the songs of Zion!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can we sing the songs of the Lord while in a foreign land?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I forget you, O Jerusalem, may my right hand forget its skill.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;May my tongue cling to the roof of my mouth if I do not remember you,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I do not consider Jerusalem my highest joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember, O Lord, what the Edomites did on the day Jerusalem fell.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tear it down,&amp;rdquo; they cried, &amp;ldquo;tear it down to its foundations!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;O Daughter of Babylon, doomed to destruction,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;happy is he who repays you for what you have done to us&amp;ndash;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He who seizes your infants and dashes them against the rocks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Psalm 137:1-9, NIV.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:12:56 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1200 - 1000 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelites-emergence-as-a-people/&#34;&gt;Israelites emerge as a distinct group of people&lt;/a&gt;, possibly organized in tribes or a league of tribes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kingship - first kings: Saul, then David, then Solomon, who built the temple of Jerusalem. After the death of Solomon, tensions between northern and southern tribes in Israel lead to the establishment of two separate kingdoms—the kingdom of Israel, composed of the ten northern tribes, with its capital eventually at Samaria, and the kingdom of Judah, composed of two southern tribes, with its capital at Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;721-722 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assyrians overrun the kingdom of Israel, deporting the ten tribes to the rest of the Assyrian Empire - lost forever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;586 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaldeans defeats Assyria, conquers the kingdom of Judah, destroys Jerusalem. Upper-class people from Jerusalem are deported to Babylon - Psalm 137 is their lament: &lt;a href=&#34;../babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/&#34;&gt;Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;539 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Babylon falls to Persian empire. The Persians destroy the Chaldean kingdom and allow the people of Judah to return to Jerusalem and rebuild their city and Temple. The revived kingdom of Judah remains under Persian control until the conquests of Alexander the Great in the fourth century B.C.E.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamia - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 07:07:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the language and concepts used, it seems clear that the gods had established not just individual rulers but an institution, with specific functions, which would outlast individual rulers—we can call this a state. It was symbolized by &lt;em&gt;‘sceptre, tiara and [shepherd’s] crook’&lt;/em&gt;; these ‘lay deposited before Anu in heaven’ before ‘kingship descended from heaven’. Among the fundamental cosmic and cultural essences were &lt;em&gt;‘the exalted and enduring crown, the throne of kingship, the exalted scepter, the royal insignia, the exalted shrine, shepherd-ship, kingship’&lt;/em&gt;. Kingship was bala; that is, ‘return or reversion to origin’, or ‘term of office’. This sounds like the prototype of the Irano-Islamic notion of the state (dawla). Thus, it seems, theology led, or enabled, people to formulate the abstract concept of an authority that would transcend the vagaries and misfortunes of individual monarchs, and so provide a more effective political instrument for human survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Egypt - Middle Kingdom</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-middle-kingdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 06:32:18 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-middle-kingdom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Middle Kingdom: 2010 - 1630 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12th to 13th dynasties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Middle Kingdom was characterized by a new concern of the pharaohs for the people. In the Old Kingdom, the pharaoh had been viewed as an inaccessible god-king. Now he was portrayed as the shepherd of his people with the responsibility to build public works and provide for the public welfare. Pharaohs of the Middle Kingdom undertook a number of helpful projects, such as draining the swampland in the Nile Delta to provide thousands of acres of new farmland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Middle Kingdom came to an end around 1630 B.C.E. with the invasion of Egypt by a people from western Asia known to the Egyptians as the Hyksos. The Hyksos used horse-drawn war chariots and overwhelmed the Egyptian soldiers, who fought from donkey carts. For almost a hundred years, the Hyksos ruled much of Egypt, but the conquered took much from their conquerors. From the Hyksos, the Egyptians learned to use bronze in making new farming tools and weapons. They also mastered the military skills of the Hyksos, especially the use of horse-drawn war chariots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, a new line of pharaohs—the eighteenth dynasty—made use of the new weapons to throw off Hyksos domination, reunite Egypt, establish the New Kingdom, and launch the Egyptians along a new militaristic path. During the period of the New Kingdom, Egypt created an empire and became the most powerful state in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-old-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - Old Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-new-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - New Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Egypt - Old Kingdom</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-old-kingdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 06:32:10 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-old-kingdom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Old Kingdom: 2575 - 2125 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4th to 8th dynasties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the fourth dynasty, a bureaucracy with regular procedures had developed. In time, Egypt was divided into provinces or nomes, as they were later called by the Greeks—twenty-two in Upper Egypt and twenty in Lower Egypt. A governor, called a nomarch by the Greeks, was head of each nome and was responsible to the king.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2540 BC: Pyramid of Giza built under King Khufu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-middle-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - Middle Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-new-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - New Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Egypt - New Kingdom</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-new-kingdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 06:31:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-new-kingdom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the period of the New Kingdom, Egypt created an empire and became the most powerful state in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Kingdom: 1539 - 1069 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18th to 20th dynasties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The power of the New Kingdom pharaohs was aided by massive wealth, which they showed by building new temples. Queen Hatshepsut (ca. 1503–1480 B.C.E.), one of the first women to become pharaoh in her own right, built a great temple at Deir el Bahri near Thebes. Hatshepsut was succeeded by her nephew, Thutmosis III (ca. 1480–1450 B.C.E.), who led seventeen military campaigns into Syria and Canaan and even reached the Euphrates River. Egyptian forces occupied Canaan and Syria and also moved westward into Libya.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amenhotep IV (1364 - 1347 BCE) and his wife Nefertiti introduced the worship of Aten, god of the sun disk, as the supreme god and later in his reign as the only god. He changed his name to Akhenaten (servant of Aten). Akhenaten’s preoccupation with his religious revolution caused him to ignore foreign affairs and led to the loss of both Syria and Canaan. Akhenaten’s changes were soon undone after his death by the boy-pharaoh Tutankhamun, who restored the old gods. The eighteenth dynasty soon came to an end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The nineteenth dynasty managed to restore Egyptian power one more time. Under Ramesses II (ca. 1279–1213 B.C.E.), the Egyptians regained control of Canaan, but new invasions in the thirteenth century by the “Sea Peoples,” as the Egyptians called them, destroyed Egyptian power in Canaan and drove the Egyptians back within their old frontiers. The days of Egyptian empire were ended, and the New Kingdom itself expired with the end of the twentieth dynasty in 1069 B.C.E. For the next thousand years, despite periodic revivals of strength, Egypt was dominated by Libyans, Nubians, Persians, and finally Macedonians after the conquest of Alexander the Great. In the first century B.C.E., Egypt became a province in Rome’s mighty empire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-old-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - Old Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-middle-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - Middle Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millenium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 03:21:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd millenium BCE – guilt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Personification of a man’s luck and ability to effectively think and act is identified with some known figure of the pantheon, usually a minor deity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sumerian composition: “Man and his God”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Man complains that what he knows does not come out right, what he says quite truthfully turns out to be false, he does things in all innocence and finds that he has been duped into committing wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His god – his powers of clear and fast thinking – is not there to suggest an answer when friends deceive him, or when evil-doers abuse him; his god has abandoned him and lost interest in him&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realization: blame lies with himself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plead: no man is perfect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He asks to be shown his faults, his transgressions, that he may confess them before his god and be forgiven; God is moved by his contrition and takes him back into favour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insight gained in the preceding millennium that the divine stands for, and upholds, a moral law -&amp;gt; is now bearing fruit in a realization of individual human responsibility, but also of innate human inability to live up to that responsibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 4th millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millenium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 03:20:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd millenium BCE – the sword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
As the settled areas of the country grew and joined, the protection that had been afforded by relative isolation was no longer there and fear of enemy attack, death or slavery, became a part of life ever present in the depth of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rise of great city-walls that around the towns in this period - the staggering amount of labor that must have gone into them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a shield against danger men looked to the now vitally important institutions of collective security, the great leagues and their officers, and particularly to the new institution of kingship as it took form and grew under the pressures of these years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gods, seen as kings and rulers, were no longer powers in nature only, they became powers in human affairs – in history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 4th millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 4th millenium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 01:39:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4th millenium BCE – famine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The powers to whom they turned were powers in and behind their primary economics on which life depended: fishing, herding, agriculture, as even the briefest look at the character of the chief gods of their cities will show. Aim and purpose of their cults were to insure the presence of these essential powers for fertility produce, and food. Houses – temples – were built for them so that they might dwell with men as members of the human community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i.e. ziggurats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this seems to be true of egyptian temples as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>