<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>daoism on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/daoism/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (daoism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/daoism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>China - Government by Non-Intervention</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;legalism1-and-daoism2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principal text: Guanzi (管子)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By being ‘empty and still’, the emperor is supposed to be able to identify the ‘regulatory principles’ of the Dao which operate in both the natural and the human worlds. The &lt;em&gt;Guanzi&lt;/em&gt; insisted that ‘statutes, regulations, and measures be modeled on the Dao’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the right laws, in harmony with the cosmic principles, are in place, then the ruler just has to leave everyone to follow them. The actual business of government is in the hands of the chief minister and bureaucracy. This may be compared to Max Weber&amp;rsquo;s notion of a rule-bound bureaucracy (which he saw as characteristic of a modern state) under a charismatic head. It is bureaucrats who govern while the monarch maintains a ‘mystical link to the cosmic flow’: ‘administration is not his business’ (Lüshi Chunqiu, in ST 237). The ruler does not need to make personal decisions as such. As Shen Bu-Hai first put it, ‘he does not act, yet as a result of his non-action the world brings itself to a state of complete order’ (in Creel 1974: 64).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;entrapped-sovereign&#34;&gt;Entrapped Sovereign&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Fei shared his predecessors’ view of the ruler as the pivot of sociopolitical order, the sole guarantor of stability and prosperity of his subjects; yet he was also bitterly aware of the ruler’s inadequacy. The very fact that the monarch—unlike his officials—owes his position to pedigree alone means that this position will more often than not be occupied by a mediocrity. Multiple historical examples scattered throughout &lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; unequivocally demonstrate how devastating the ruler’s ineptitude can be. The intrinsic contradiction between an &lt;em&gt;institutionally infallible and humanly erring sovereign&lt;/em&gt; is the major source of tension in the Han Feizi (Pines 2013b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations: remain empty and tranquil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruler does not reveal his desires; should he do so, the minister will carve and embellish them. He does not reveal his views; should he do so, the minister will use them to present his different [opinion]. … The way of the enlightened sovereign is to let the knowledgeable completely exhaust their contemplations—then the ruler relies on them to decide on matters and is not depleted of knowledge; to let the worthy utilize their talents—then the ruler relies on them, assigns tasks, and is not depleted of abilities. When there is success, the ruler possesses a worthy [name]; when there is failure, the minister bears the responsibility. (&lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; 5: 27)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the paradox of the entrapped sovereign, who enjoys God-like omnipotence, but who is required to refrain from any activism in order to preserve this omnipotence - a manifestation of the intrinsic contradiction of the authoritarian system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Pines, Yuri, &amp;ldquo;Legalism in Chinese Philosophy&amp;rdquo;, The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Winter 2018 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), URL = &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&#34;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daoism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/daoism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 07:07:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/daoism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Laozi: Confucius&amp;rsquo;s contemporary. Daoism is authored in 道德经.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laozi proposed a return to primitive simplicity, withdrawal from the world, spontaneity. They thought that society had become overdeveloped, overheated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;The more prohibitions and rules, the poorer the people become&amp;hellip; The more elaborate the laws, the more they commit crimes&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corruption and oppression were the inevitable results of civilization and were brought about precisely by those whom others idealized—rulers and sages. In this view, the state is part of the problem, part of humanity’s misguided attempt to control the world. Solutions to human problems are to be sought only in the individual mind. This was the counter-culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;monarchy&#34;&gt;Monarchy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Daoists thought that the sage-ruler is himself &amp;lsquo;the unmoving director of the world&amp;rsquo;: his beneficence consists in going with the flow of events, like water flowing downhill; Laozi spoke of a sage-ruler perfectly in tune with Heaven and Earth, and with &amp;lsquo;the hearts and minds of the people&amp;rsquo;. &amp;lsquo;When he acts, he takes no credit&amp;rsquo;, for &amp;lsquo;the people say &amp;ldquo;we did it ourselves&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../china-government-by-non-intervention/&#34;&gt;China - Government by Non-Intervention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>