<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mesopotamia on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/mesopotamia/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (mesopotamia)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 14:39:36 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/mesopotamia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lament for Ur</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-lament-for-ur/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 14:39:36 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-lament-for-ur/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some extracts from the Lament for Ur, in which the goddess of Ur, Ningal, tells how she pleaded with the divine assembly, but to no avail, and the consequent destruction of Ur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then verily, to the assembly,&lt;br&gt;
where the crowd had not yet risen,&lt;br&gt;
while the Anunnaki, binding themselves&lt;br&gt;
(to uphold the decision), were still seated,&lt;br&gt;
I dragged my feet and I stretched out my arms,&lt;br&gt;
truly I shed my tears in front of An.&lt;br&gt;
Truly I myself mourned in front of Enlil:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;May my city not be destroyed!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
I said indeed to them.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;May Ur not be destroyed!&amp;rdquo; I said indeed to them.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;And may its people not be killed!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
I said indeed to them.&lt;br&gt;
But An never bent towards those words,&lt;br&gt;
and Enlil never with an, &amp;ldquo;It is pleasing, so be it!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
did soothe my heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Behold,) they gave instruction&lt;br&gt;
that the city be destroyed,&lt;br&gt;
(behold,) they gave instruction&lt;br&gt;
that Ur be destroyed,&lt;br&gt;
and as its destiny decreed&lt;br&gt;
that its inhabitants be killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city is doomed, and the execution of the terrible decree is left to Enlil. Stating in plain terms what we know happened we could say that wild mountaineers from the East - Elam and the Sua people - invaded Sumer, besieged Ur, and, when eventually the inhabitants surrendered the city, sacked and burned it mercilessly. But plain terms would be entirely inadequate to convey what the Sumerians knew took place. In a cosmic sense it was Enlil&amp;rsquo;s own destructive essence expressed in his element the storm that destroyed Ur. The wild hordes from the mountains were but incidental form in which that essence clothed itself, the reality was Enlil&amp;rsquo;s storm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enlil called the storm.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Winds of abundance he took from the land.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good winds he took away from Sumer.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Deputed evil winds.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Entrusted them to Kingaluda, tender of storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He called the storm that annihilates the land.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
He called disastrous winds.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Enlil - choosing Gibil as his helper -&lt;br&gt;
called the (great) hurricane of heaven.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
The (blinding) hurricane howling across the skies -&lt;br&gt;
the people mourn -&lt;br&gt;
the storm that annihilates the land roaring over the earth -&lt;br&gt;
the people mourn -&lt;br&gt;
the tempest unsubduable like breaks through levees,&lt;br&gt;
beats down upon, devours the city&amp;rsquo;s ships,&lt;br&gt;
(all these) he gathered at the base of heaven.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Great) fires he lit that heralded the storm.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
And lit on either flank of furious winds&lt;br&gt;
the searing heat of desert.&lt;br&gt;
Like flaming heat of noon this fire scorched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this storm that destroys the city:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm ordered by Enlil in hate,&lt;br&gt;
the storm which wears away the country,&lt;br&gt;
covered Ur like a cloth,&lt;br&gt;
veiled it like a linen sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it clears away all is over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that day did the storm leave the city;&lt;br&gt;
that city was a ruin.&lt;br&gt;
O father Nanna, that town was left a ruin.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
On that day did the storm leave the country.&lt;br&gt;
The people mourn.&lt;br&gt;
Its people(&amp;lsquo;s corpses), not potsherds,&lt;br&gt;
littered the approaches.&lt;br&gt;
The walls were gaping;&lt;br&gt;
the high gates, the roads,&lt;br&gt;
were piled with dead.&lt;br&gt;
In the wide streets,&lt;br&gt;
where feasting crowds (once) gathered&lt;br&gt;
jumbled they lay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all the streets and roadways bodies lay.&lt;br&gt;
In open fields that used to fill with dancers,&lt;br&gt;
the people lay in heaps.&lt;br&gt;
The country&amp;rsquo;s blood now filled its holes,&lt;br&gt;
like metal in a mold;&lt;br&gt;
bodies dissolved - like butter left in the sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;] In reality, then, justice - that is to say, human justice - quails before the absolute authority of the unanimous will of the gods; they are not to be challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descent of Innana</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-descent-of-innana/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 14:21:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-descent-of-innana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The story begins with a whim, a sudden desire of Inanna for the netherworld, a desire that comes to rule her to the exclusion of everything else:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She set her heart from highest heaven&lt;br&gt;
on earth&amp;rsquo;s deepest ground,&lt;br&gt;
the goddess set her heart from highest heaven&lt;br&gt;
on earth&amp;rsquo;s deepest ground,&lt;br&gt;
Inanna set her heart from highest heaven&lt;br&gt;
on earth&amp;rsquo;s deepest ground,&lt;br&gt;
milady abandoned heaven, abandoned earth,&lt;br&gt;
went down to Hades,&lt;br&gt;
Inanna abandoned heaven, abandoned earth,&lt;br&gt;
went down to Hades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when she comes up to find a substitute for her death, she sees her husband enjoying himself. And so she gives the deputies of death their head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She looked at him, it was a look of death,&lt;br&gt;
spoke to them, it was a word of wrath&lt;br&gt;
cried out to them, it was the cry of &amp;ldquo;guilty!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Take this one along!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
Holy Inanna gave the shepherd Dumuzi into their hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sumerian Wedding Texts</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-wedding-texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 13:40:01 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-wedding-texts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-the-cultivators-wedding-text&#34;&gt;1. The cultivators&amp;rsquo; wedding text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The sequence of the nuptial drama is thus clear, but a great deal of the meaning of the text remains dark and unexplained. To understand this we must understand what the powers stand for.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bride, Inanna, represents the numen of the communal storehouse for dates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bridegroom, Dumuzi, represents what is to be stored in the storehouse - the power behind the yearly burgeoning of the palm and its producing its yield of dates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, for example, is the odd &amp;ldquo;gem-revealing heap&amp;rdquo;?&lt;br&gt;
Why do Inanna&amp;rsquo;s wedding ornaments come from it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That a heap of fresh dates should furnish the ornaments for Inanna is logical since freshly harvested dates are the pride and adornment of the bare shelves of a storehouse for dates. The date clusters that are to adorn the shelves of the storehouse become ritually experienced as traditional feminine adornments and jewelry such as would be suitable for decking out a human bride, and the heap from thich they are taken comes close to becoming ajewel shrine of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is Dumuzi to be taken back to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That these two powers are wed means that the power for fertility and yield has been captured by the numen of the storehouse - and so by the community - and has become its trusty provider for all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dumuzi is safely in the storehouse, and the community revels in abundant food and drink, release from anxiety and fear of starvation, blissfully secure from want. Inanna expresses the communal feeling precisely: not love or the raptures of passion mark her wedding night, but a gently glowing sense of inner and outer bliss in trust and security:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not only is it sweet to sleep hand in hand with him,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sweetest of sweet is too the loveliness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;of joining heart to heart with him.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-later-developments-of-the-cultivators-wedding-text&#34;&gt;2. Later developments of the cultivators&amp;rsquo; wedding text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of blessings expected increases. Now it ranges from  the yields of farmers and shepherds to the take of fishermen and fowlers, from the wildlife in woods and marshes to the produce of vineyards and gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contrasts with the first cultic wedding text, the Uruk Text. There the god, Dumuzi-Amaushumgalanna, was the power in the fertility and yield of the date palm only, and the underlying ritual was a date harvest ritual and nothing else. This concentration on a single major economy is, we should judge, an original feature, but as the cities drew a variety of economies into their orbit - Uruk, for instance, seems to have united several settlements of date growers, oxherders, and shepherds - the purview of the cult broadened so as to make its god stand for a general fertility and yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a broadening is already suggested on the Uruk Vase of the outgoing fourth millennium where the bridal gifts brought by the god include not only dates but ears of grain and sheep heavy with wool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Different portrayals of this economic diversification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumuzi is a shepherd; the farmer, the fishermen, and the fowler are wedding attendants, bringing gifts of their product to supplement what the shepherd provides.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dumuzi is both a shepherd and farmer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-the-herders-wedding-text&#34;&gt;3. The herders&amp;rsquo; wedding text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the song Inanna, glorying in her young body, which has just attained puberty, sings the praises of her pubic triangle with its as yet sparse growth of hairs, comparing it first to a metal enchasement with decorative studs sticking out like linchpins in a cartwheel, then to a ceremonial barge called the &amp;ldquo;Barge of Heaven&amp;rdquo; (the recent hairs she sees as mooring ropes holding the barge), and the image leads over into that of the cosmic barge of heaven, the crescent of the new moon. Next her triangle has become a virginal plot in the desert, not yet cultivated, then again a stubble field on which ducks have been put out to be fattened, black hairs dotting it like black ducks against light dun soil, then it is a high-lying field, hillock land, piled up with levees, well watered in readiness for ploughing - she has just bathed in water - and then moist lowlands similarly readied. Since a woman, though she may own fields, cannot herself plough them but must seek a ploughman to do it for her, the song ends with the question of who he should be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;My enchased parts so nailed down&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;as (with) linchpins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;attached to a big cart,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(my crescent-shaped) &amp;ldquo;Barge of Heaven,&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;so (well) belayed,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;full of loveliness, like the new moon,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my untilled plot,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;left so fallow in the desert,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my duck field so studded with ducks,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my hillock land, so (well) watered,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;my parts, piled up with levees,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(well) watered&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I, being (but) a maiden,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;who will be their ploughman?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My parts, (well) watered lowlands,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I, being (but) a lady,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;who will put (plough) oxen to them?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the elegist responds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Young lady, may the king plough them for you!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;May the king, Dumuzi, plough them for you!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is obviously the right answer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;The man of my heart! The ploughman is the man of my heart!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Herder Wedding Text&amp;rdquo; ends on much the same note as the other wedding texts, with delight in great abundances of food. Yet, there is one subtle difference. The riches here garnered by Inanna - milk and milk products - are short-term only. They will not, like the more durable riches of the date harvest, last through an approaching dry season and free the community from want until the next season. The sense of having reached security which informs the wedding texts of Amaushumgalanna can have little relevance in the herder&amp;rsquo;s world with its swiftly passing blessings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That world has, rather, its own set of relevant experiences. In spring the desert fills with green, the herds gambol in the pastures and mate, and from that mating flows the herder&amp;rsquo;s prosperity; increase of flocks and herds, newborn lambs, kids, and calves, plentiful milk from the full udders of the mother animals. In the herder&amp;rsquo;s view the emphasis of the sacred marriage is therefore on its mating aspect. He sees it as a divine engendering which brings into being spring&amp;rsquo;s glorious burst, the sacred cosmic sexual act in which all nature is fertilized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This emphasis comes through clearly in Inanna&amp;rsquo;s frank praise of her private parts with its central image of the field ready for the fertilizing seed plough - an image, incidentally, which still does not take us outside the herder&amp;rsquo;s world since the plough oxen were provided by the cowherders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the orchardman&amp;rsquo;s and the herder&amp;rsquo;s rite of the sacred marriage differ fundamentally. The first is a harvest rite binding the date palm&amp;rsquo;s power for fertility and yield to the numen of the storehouse in bonds of marriage and mutual love. The other is a fertility rite uniting - by incarnating them in human actors - the divine powers for fertility and new life in a generative sexual embrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deadly Diseases</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-deadly-diseases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 13:37:07 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/poem-deadly-diseases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The shivers and chills (of death)
that fritter the sum of things,
spawn of the god of heaven,
spawned on an evil spirit,
the death warrants, beloved sons of the storm god,
born of the queen of the netherworld,
who were torn out of heaven and hurled from the earth as castoffs, are creatures of hell, all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up above they roar, down below they cheep,
they are the bitter venom of the gods,
they are the great storms let loose from heaven,
they are the owl (of ill omen) that hoots in the town,
spawn spawned by the god of heaven, sons born by earth
are they.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over high roofs, over broad roofs like a floodwave
they surge,
from house to house they climb over,
Doors do not hold them, locks do not restrain them,
through the doors they glide like snakes,
through the hinge boxes they blow like wind.
From the man&amp;rsquo;s embrace they lead off the wife,
from the man&amp;rsquo;s knee they make the child get up,
and the youth they fetch out of the house of his in-laws,
they are the numbness, the daze,
that tread on the heels of man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;Most Ancient Verse&lt;/em&gt;. The University of Chicago Press, 1963.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian Irrigation</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-irrigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 13:24:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-irrigation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The annual flood cycle of ancient Mesopotamia was poorly synchronised with the needs of the cultivators; in contrast to the Nile, whose monsoon-driven annual flood well matches the need of irrigation, the annual flood of both the Tigris and Euphrates peaks in the late spring, or early summer, as a result of winter rainfall and spring snowmelt on the mountains of Anatolia, Iran and Iraq. This not only threatens the ripening grain crops, but also requires that considerable efforts be made to protect the fields from flooding. There are scholars that suggest that the Sumerians expended more effort on flood control than in the distribution of water for irrigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Referencs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Crawford, Harriet. &lt;em&gt;The Sumerian World&lt;/em&gt;. Routledge, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 12:56:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development through fourth - second millennium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;give us this day our daily bread&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;preserve us from evil&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;forgive me, father, for i have sinned&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &lt;em&gt;The Treasures of Darkness&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transnational Diplomacy and Trade in 14th Century BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 04:36:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Region: West Asia and Mediterranean&lt;br&gt;
Time: 14th century BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This Late Bronze Age was an age of superpowers. The great pharaohs of the Eighteenth Dynasty had transformed Egypt into a conquering state, and the Hittites had created an empire out of the disparate city-states and kingdoms of Anatolia. The Assyrians controlled Near Eastern trade, and the Kassite kingdom of Babylonia remained a significant force in economic and military relationships. In addition to these imperial entities, numerous smaller states also flourished and extended their influence westward into the Mediterranean. Holding it all together was a network of trade routes that created an interdependent Afro-Eurasian world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational diplomacy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../amarna-letter-ea4/&#34;&gt;letters between rulers/elites&lt;/a&gt;, found in Akhenaten&amp;rsquo;s abandoned capital of Akhetaten (modern el-Amarna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marriage contracts between rulers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other lavish gifts (greeting gifts for festivals and such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptians delighted in Canaanite glass, Greeks prized Egyptian amulets, and the merchants of Syria admired Greek pottery and wool.
This was the background for the development of the abjad (the consonant-only family of alphabet later giving rise to the Phoenician alphabet). Ugarit, on the coast of modern-day Syria, developed the Ugaritic alphabet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian vs Egyptian Kingship</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-vs-egyptian-kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 07:10:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-vs-egyptian-kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Never in Mesopotamia was his relationship with god so close as in Egypt; no Mesopotamian king was deified. In both cultures the image of the king as shepherd of the people was developed. The king’s duty to implement justice, especially by fair adjudication between the powerful and the weak, was emphasized in both cultures, perhaps more insistently in Egypt. The most striking contrast was the judicial and, occasionally, political role of citizens in Mesopotamia, and the complete absence of such popular participation in Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamia-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamia - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Egypt - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamia - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 07:07:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the language and concepts used, it seems clear that the gods had established not just individual rulers but an institution, with specific functions, which would outlast individual rulers—we can call this a state. It was symbolized by &lt;em&gt;‘sceptre, tiara and [shepherd’s] crook’&lt;/em&gt;; these ‘lay deposited before Anu in heaven’ before ‘kingship descended from heaven’. Among the fundamental cosmic and cultural essences were &lt;em&gt;‘the exalted and enduring crown, the throne of kingship, the exalted scepter, the royal insignia, the exalted shrine, shepherd-ship, kingship’&lt;/em&gt;. Kingship was bala; that is, ‘return or reversion to origin’, or ‘term of office’. This sounds like the prototype of the Irano-Islamic notion of the state (dawla). Thus, it seems, theology led, or enabled, people to formulate the abstract concept of an authority that would transcend the vagaries and misfortunes of individual monarchs, and so provide a more effective political instrument for human survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 05:09:01 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3000 BCE: Emergence of Sumerian city-states&lt;br&gt;
2340 BCE: Sargon of Akkad overruns Sumerian city states, establishing Akkadian empire&lt;br&gt;
2100 BCE: Attacks from neighbouring hill peoples cause Akkadian empire to fall, bringing back independent city-states&lt;br&gt;
1792 BCE: Hammurabi&amp;rsquo;s rule from Babylon begins&lt;br&gt;
1754 BCE: Code of Hammurabi, a collection of 282 laws&lt;br&gt;
1750 BCE: Hammurabi&amp;rsquo;s rule ends&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millennium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millennium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 03:21:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millennium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd millennium BCE – guilt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rise-of-personal-religion&#34;&gt;Rise of personal religion&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personification of a man’s luck and ability to effectively think and act is identified with some known figure of the pantheon, usually a minor deity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sumerian composition: “Man and his God”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Man complains that what he knows does not come out right, what he says quite truthfully turns out to be false, he does things in all innocence and finds that he has been duped into committing wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His god – his powers of clear and fast thinking – is not there to suggest an answer when friends deceive him, or when evil-doers abuse him; his god has abandoned him and lost interest in him&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realization: blame lies with himself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plead: no man is perfect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He asks to be shown his faults, his transgressions, that he may confess them before his god and be forgiven; God is moved by his contrition and takes him back into favour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insight gained in the preceding millennium that the divine stands for, and upholds, a moral law -&amp;gt; is now bearing fruit in a realization of individual human responsibility, but also of innate human inability to live up to that responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;many are my iniquities, slip them off (me) like a garment.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uses-and-expands-the-metaphor-of-the-god-as-parent&#34;&gt;&amp;hellip;uses and expands the metaphor of the god as parent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner &amp;ldquo;form&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;metaphor&amp;rdquo; of the parent, of &amp;ldquo;father&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;mother&amp;rdquo; under which the personal god came to be seen, serves as psychologically possible bridge to the great and terrifying awesome cosmic powers. For it is within human experience that even the highest, greatest, and most terrifying personages in society have a mild, human, and approachable side in their relations to their children. Children, in their immediacy, their certainty of being loved, can overcome - being entirely unaware of it - the terror and awe of power and status precisely because they seek and see only the personal in the relation. Thus the possibility that even the cosmic powers could be personal gods, could have an unfrightening, loving, ever-forgiving side toward their little human children, is psychologically conceivable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if we can thus, by following personal religion back to its original setting, see more clearly how its attitude could be psychologically possible, this does not change or remove the original and basic paradox with all its inherent contradictions. As the attitude began to permeate religion generally, as it could be assumed not only toward one&amp;rsquo;s personal god, but toward any god, even the one and only God, it was inevitable that its paradoxical nature should become apparent. There is a stage in childhood when parents are all-powerful and divine to the child. The child (to grow up) has eventually to adjust to the disturbing realization that parents are after all only other human beings with human limitations. But in this case such adjustment was excluded. The divine parents were, and had to remain, divine. Thus experience could not but drive its cruel wedge ever more deeply between the dispassionate, terrifying, cosmic aspect of the divine which governed the way things really are and really happen, and the personal, concerned, angry, forgiving, loving aspect in which I, the individual, matter so profoundly that love for me must sway the uni- verse off its course to help and sustain me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the problem of the righteous sufferer. It forces itself upon religious consciousness in Mesopotamia about the middle of the second millennium and is dealt with in two remarkable works, Ludlul bel nemeqi (&amp;ldquo;Let me praise the expert&amp;rdquo;) and the Babylonian Theodicy. In the first of these we hear about a man, pious and righteous, who nevertheless falls on evil days:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alu-disease has clothed itself in my body&lt;br&gt;
like a garment;&lt;br&gt;
sleep in a net enmeshes me;&lt;br&gt;
my eyes stare but see not,&lt;br&gt;
my ears are open, but hear not;&lt;br&gt;
weakness has seized all my body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unfeeling, cosmic aspect of the divine is taking its course with no regard for him at all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No god came to my aid, or grasped my hand,&lt;br&gt;
my goddess did not pity me,&lt;br&gt;
walked not at my side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the incomprehensibility of the ways of the universe, of its failure to take account of him, is so great that he can only escape in doubt about himself and his own powers of judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What seems good to oneself,&lt;br&gt;
is a crime before the god.&lt;br&gt;
What to one&amp;rsquo;s heart seems bad,&lt;br&gt;
is good before one&amp;rsquo;s god.&lt;br&gt;
Who may comprehend the minds of gods&lt;br&gt;
in heaven&amp;rsquo;s depth?&lt;br&gt;
The thoughts of (those) divine deep waters,&lt;br&gt;
who could fathom them?&lt;br&gt;
How could mankind, beclouded,&lt;br&gt;
comprehend the ways of gods?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contradictions are indeed insoluble as long as the attitude of personal religion is allowed to reduce existence, the infinite universe, to the narrow compass of a personal world, and expect it to center in an individual and his personal needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A significant step toward a solution was only made later, in the middle of the first millennium, by the religious genius of Israel: the treatment of the problem in the Book of Job. Here, in God&amp;rsquo;s speech, the imbalance is redressed. The personal, egocentric view of the sufferer - however righteous - is rejected. The self-importance which demands that the universe adjust to his needs; his righteousness, is cast aside, and the full stature of God as the majestic creator and ruler of the universe is reinstated. The distance between the cosmic and the personal, between God in his infinite greatness and mere individual man, is so great and so decisive that an individual has no rights, not even to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millennium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 4th millennium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millennium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millennium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 03:20:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millennium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd millennium BCE – the sword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
As the settled areas of the country grew and joined, the protection that had been afforded by relative isolation was no longer there and fear of enemy attack, death or slavery, became a part of life ever present in the depth of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rise of great city-walls that around the towns in this period - the staggering amount of labor that must have gone into them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a shield against danger men looked to the now vitally important institutions of collective security, the great leagues and their officers, and particularly to the new institution of kingship as it took form and grew under the pressures of these years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence suggests that kingship originally was a temporary office: a king was chosen as leader when war threatened and ceased to exercise authority once the emergency was over. Now, the emergency had become chronic, and the office of king had become permanent because of it, so had his army and the manning and maintenance of the city wall. Gradually, leadership in all major communal undertakings devolved on the king and became united in his person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grafting-the-ruler-metaphor-onto-the-gods&#34;&gt;Grafting the ruler metaphor onto the gods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruler metaphor - expressed in the terms &amp;ldquo;master,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;lord,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;warrior&amp;rdquo; - fits particularly well the unbounded power of the natural phenomenon in which the god is experienced, and the prayer cogently conveys awe before the wholly other, the terrifying power in the flood-wave sweeping down from the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;implications-for-their-worldview-cosmos-as-polity&#34;&gt;Implications for their worldview: cosmos as polity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruler metaphor – like the ruler concept - could not be lifted out of the social and political context from which it derived its meaning. The new view of the gods as rulers brought the whole political context of the ruler to bear on them and thus - since they were the powers in all the significant phenomena around - on the whole phenomenal world. The universe became a polity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most major gods held office and had roles to play&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases these roles were essentially the old ways of the fertility powers, but they are now less expressions of the gods&amp;rsquo; innate natures than charges conferred on them by a high-ranking god such as An or Enlil, or by the assembly of the gods as a whole. Thus Ningirsu/Ninurta, the power in the spring thunderstorms is not merely expressing his inner essence, he is fulfilling his duties in a cosmic office: he is Enlil&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;warrior&amp;rdquo; doing battle for him with the highlands. Similarly, Enki, god of the fresh waters in rivers and marshes, is no longer merely the power for fertility in those waters. He is an official charged by An with such duties as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clear the pure mouths of the Tigris and&lt;br&gt;
Euphrates, to make verdure plentiful,&lt;br&gt;
make dense the clouds, grant water in abundance&lt;br&gt;
to all ploughlands,&lt;br&gt;
to make grain lift its head in furrows&lt;br&gt;
and to make pasture abundant in the desert,&lt;br&gt;
to make young saplings in plantations and in orchards&lt;br&gt;
sprout where planted like a forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enlil himself is no longer the power in the wind, &amp;ldquo;Lord Wind,&amp;rdquo; but has charge of all winds and has them do his bidding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-growing-paradox-the-gods-new-function-of-upholding-justice-derived-from-the-role-of-ruler-and-that-human-justice-may-not-be-upheld&#34;&gt;A growing paradox: the god&amp;rsquo;s new function of upholding justice, derived from the role of &amp;ldquo;ruler&amp;rdquo;, and that human justice may not be upheld.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a href=&#34;../poem-lament-for-ur/&#34;&gt;Lament for Ur&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;[&amp;hellip;] In reality, then, justice - that is to say, human justice - quails before the absolute authority of the unanimous will of the gods; they are not to be challenged.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gods, seen as kings and rulers, were no longer powers in nature only, they became powers in human affairs – in history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millennium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 4th millennium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 4th millennium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-4th-millennium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 01:39:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-4th-millennium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4th millennium BCE – famine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Early Mesopotamian economy was precarious and uncertain, based on &lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-irrigation/&#34;&gt;artificial irrigation&lt;/a&gt;, and the powers to whom they turned were the powers in and behind their primary economics on which life depended: herding, agriculture(, and fishing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim and purpose of their cults were to insure the presence of these essential powers for fertility, produce, and food. Houses – temples – were built for them so that they might dwell with men as members of the human community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i.e. ziggurats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this seems to be true of egyptian temples as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../poem-deadly-diseases/&#34;&gt;meditations on death&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../poem-wedding-texts/&#34;&gt;wedding texts - an example of how the economic setting shaped the rite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../poem-descent-of-innana/&#34;&gt;depiction of winter starvation in a poem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millennium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millennium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millennium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>