<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>legalism on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/legalism/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (legalism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/legalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>China - Government by Non-Intervention</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;legalism1-and-daoism2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principal text: Guanzi (管子)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By being ‘empty and still’, the emperor is supposed to be able to identify the ‘regulatory principles’ of the Dao which operate in both the natural and the human worlds. The &lt;em&gt;Guanzi&lt;/em&gt; insisted that ‘statutes, regulations, and measures be modeled on the Dao’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the right laws, in harmony with the cosmic principles, are in place, then the ruler just has to leave everyone to follow them. The actual business of government is in the hands of the chief minister and bureaucracy. This may be compared to Max Weber&amp;rsquo;s notion of a rule-bound bureaucracy (which he saw as characteristic of a modern state) under a charismatic head. It is bureaucrats who govern while the monarch maintains a ‘mystical link to the cosmic flow’: ‘administration is not his business’ (Lüshi Chunqiu, in ST 237). The ruler does not need to make personal decisions as such. As Shen Bu-Hai first put it, ‘he does not act, yet as a result of his non-action the world brings itself to a state of complete order’ (in Creel 1974: 64).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;entrapped-sovereign&#34;&gt;Entrapped Sovereign&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Fei shared his predecessors’ view of the ruler as the pivot of sociopolitical order, the sole guarantor of stability and prosperity of his subjects; yet he was also bitterly aware of the ruler’s inadequacy. The very fact that the monarch—unlike his officials—owes his position to pedigree alone means that this position will more often than not be occupied by a mediocrity. Multiple historical examples scattered throughout &lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; unequivocally demonstrate how devastating the ruler’s ineptitude can be. The intrinsic contradiction between an &lt;em&gt;institutionally infallible and humanly erring sovereign&lt;/em&gt; is the major source of tension in the Han Feizi (Pines 2013b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations: remain empty and tranquil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruler does not reveal his desires; should he do so, the minister will carve and embellish them. He does not reveal his views; should he do so, the minister will use them to present his different [opinion]. … The way of the enlightened sovereign is to let the knowledgeable completely exhaust their contemplations—then the ruler relies on them to decide on matters and is not depleted of knowledge; to let the worthy utilize their talents—then the ruler relies on them, assigns tasks, and is not depleted of abilities. When there is success, the ruler possesses a worthy [name]; when there is failure, the minister bears the responsibility. (&lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; 5: 27)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the paradox of the entrapped sovereign, who enjoys God-like omnipotence, but who is required to refrain from any activism in order to preserve this omnipotence - a manifestation of the intrinsic contradiction of the authoritarian system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Pines, Yuri, &amp;ldquo;Legalism in Chinese Philosophy&amp;rdquo;, The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Winter 2018 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), URL = &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&#34;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legalism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/legalism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 07:06:58 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/legalism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A ruler undertakes policies which, even though ‘people do not have the sense to rejoice in them’, are for their long-term benefit (Han Feizi, Basic Writings, 128–9); he ‘does not indulge the people’s desires, he simply looks ahead for what will benefit them’. The ruler may have to enforce his measures ‘against the will of the people’. The goals of the state—prosperity, stability, and expansion—were the only ones which would make life tolerable for the majority of people, and they were ones which people would choose if they could see sufficiently far ahead. This was their justification for compulsory labour, taxation, military service, and severe punishments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the reasoning behind the policy, advocated by Shang Yang and
others, and first implemented in the state of Qin, of making punishments
exceptionally severe but predictable. With what would nowadays appear
breathtaking honesty, they advocated rule by fear as the most efficient way of securing the greatest good of the greatest number (Han Feizi, Basic Writings, 104). Only when light offences are ‘regarded as serious’ do ‘serious ones have no chance of coming’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;War and killing are permissible so long as the aim is to abolish them. This means achieving what people want by means they do not want (Book of Lord Shang, 230, 285). It is only by going against the wishes of the people that you make them happy. ‘What I call punishment is the basis of righteousness, but what the world calls righteousness is the way of violence’ (Han Feizi, in Wang and Chang 1986: 46). In other words, they were implying that the outcome desired by Confucius could only be achieved by means he refused to contemplate. It simply could not be achieved by persuasion and example (Book of Lord Shang, 325). The true lesson of history was that a great king ‘seized the world by force, but held it by righteousness’—an almost prophetic statement when one looks at the first two dynasties of the Chinese empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../china-government-by-non-intervention/&#34;&gt;China - Government by Non-Intervention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>