<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>state on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/state/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (state)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/state/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>China - Government by Non-Intervention</title>
      <link>/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 20:30:14 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/china-government-by-non-intervention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;legalism1-and-daoism2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principal text: Guanzi (管子)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By being ‘empty and still’, the emperor is supposed to be able to identify the ‘regulatory principles’ of the Dao which operate in both the natural and the human worlds. The &lt;em&gt;Guanzi&lt;/em&gt; insisted that ‘statutes, regulations, and measures be modeled on the Dao’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the right laws, in harmony with the cosmic principles, are in place, then the ruler just has to leave everyone to follow them. The actual business of government is in the hands of the chief minister and bureaucracy. This may be compared to Max Weber&amp;rsquo;s notion of a rule-bound bureaucracy (which he saw as characteristic of a modern state) under a charismatic head. It is bureaucrats who govern while the monarch maintains a ‘mystical link to the cosmic flow’: ‘administration is not his business’ (Lüshi Chunqiu, in ST 237). The ruler does not need to make personal decisions as such. As Shen Bu-Hai first put it, ‘he does not act, yet as a result of his non-action the world brings itself to a state of complete order’ (in Creel 1974: 64).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;entrapped-sovereign&#34;&gt;Entrapped Sovereign&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Fei shared his predecessors’ view of the ruler as the pivot of sociopolitical order, the sole guarantor of stability and prosperity of his subjects; yet he was also bitterly aware of the ruler’s inadequacy. The very fact that the monarch—unlike his officials—owes his position to pedigree alone means that this position will more often than not be occupied by a mediocrity. Multiple historical examples scattered throughout &lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; unequivocally demonstrate how devastating the ruler’s ineptitude can be. The intrinsic contradiction between an &lt;em&gt;institutionally infallible and humanly erring sovereign&lt;/em&gt; is the major source of tension in the Han Feizi (Pines 2013b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommendations: remain empty and tranquil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruler does not reveal his desires; should he do so, the minister will carve and embellish them. He does not reveal his views; should he do so, the minister will use them to present his different [opinion]. … The way of the enlightened sovereign is to let the knowledgeable completely exhaust their contemplations—then the ruler relies on them to decide on matters and is not depleted of knowledge; to let the worthy utilize their talents—then the ruler relies on them, assigns tasks, and is not depleted of abilities. When there is success, the ruler possesses a worthy [name]; when there is failure, the minister bears the responsibility. (&lt;em&gt;Han Feizi&lt;/em&gt; 5: 27)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the paradox of the entrapped sovereign, who enjoys God-like omnipotence, but who is required to refrain from any activism in order to preserve this omnipotence - a manifestation of the intrinsic contradiction of the authoritarian system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Pines, Yuri, &amp;ldquo;Legalism in Chinese Philosophy&amp;rdquo;, The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Winter 2018 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), URL = &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&#34;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2018/entries/chinese-legalism/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:39:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social hierarchy: classical texts specified &lt;em&gt;varna&lt;/em&gt;, a system of four classes in society; this was instantiated into the caste system, &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;, where people are born into a clan (&lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;) that specifies social and economic duty, and requirements for endogamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s thought that this class system was introduced by the Aryans, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-history/&#34;&gt;when they first arrived in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophies that emerged from this background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview/&#34;&gt;Brahmanism&lt;/a&gt;, which later developed into Hinduism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of which were underwritten by the concept of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; - the sum/worth of one&amp;rsquo;s actions in life that decide one&amp;rsquo;s fate in their next life, and in brahmanism, this is accumulated through carrying out &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; - ethics, duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/&#34;&gt;Dharma vs. Artha, Morality vs. Practicality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hundred Schools of Thought</title>
      <link>/posts/hundred-schools-of-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:29:50 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/hundred-schools-of-thought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Main themes of Chinese political thought: state and monarchy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;state&#34;&gt;State&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature of scholar bureaucrats: 1. as political advisors, working in public service with a rank in the state hierarchy, they had a voice in the formation of the state; 2. as &lt;em&gt;itinerant&lt;/em&gt; political advisors, which gave them leverage and contributed to their intellectual independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no other culture would the history of thought and the history of the state be so closely intertwined. Ethical and philosophical reflection developed in response to the increasingly problematic political situation. This was the period of ‘a hundred schools’. China produced a greater variety of political ideas than any other monarchical agrarian civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;monarchy&#34;&gt;Monarchy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All Chinese theories emphasized the need for a single locus of authority, a quasi-absolute monarch, to resolve the problem of human discord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-qin-dynasty-inaugurated&#34;&gt;What Qin dynasty inaugurated&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than two millennia this imperial government seemed to have a staying-power and a power of self-renewal which one finds in religions—but less often in states—in other parts of the world. In ancient China [&amp;hellip;] ‘political thought’ had a somewhat different function from the equivalent genre elsewhere. It brought together what we in the West divide into the sacred and the secular. Religions such as Hinduism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam were similarly based on sacred texts. But these supported a system of belief and practice rather than a system of government. China was the only text-based state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;influential-belief-systems&#34;&gt;Influential belief systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../confucianism-overview/&#34;&gt;Confucianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../legalism-overview/&#34;&gt;Legalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../daoism-overview/&#34;&gt;Daoism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-china-history/&#34;&gt;Ancient China History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel - State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:35:05 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Features that have shaped Israelite political thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Untouchably high God - implications for egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Covenant - implications for political power of people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Exile - implications for human condition and suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamia - State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 07:07:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the language and concepts used, it seems clear that the gods had established not just individual rulers but an institution, with specific functions, which would outlast individual rulers—we can call this a state. It was symbolized by &lt;em&gt;‘sceptre, tiara and [shepherd’s] crook’&lt;/em&gt;; these ‘lay deposited before Anu in heaven’ before ‘kingship descended from heaven’. Among the fundamental cosmic and cultural essences were &lt;em&gt;‘the exalted and enduring crown, the throne of kingship, the exalted scepter, the royal insignia, the exalted shrine, shepherd-ship, kingship’&lt;/em&gt;. Kingship was bala; that is, ‘return or reversion to origin’, or ‘term of office’. This sounds like the prototype of the Irano-Islamic notion of the state (dawla). Thus, it seems, theology led, or enabled, people to formulate the abstract concept of an authority that would transcend the vagaries and misfortunes of individual monarchs, and so provide a more effective political instrument for human survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Egypt - State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/egypt-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 06:32:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/egypt-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;pharaoh-god-king&#34;&gt;Pharaoh, god-king&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Egypt the king was more closely identified with the gods than in any other culture. He was the incarnation of Horus and Osiris, the son of the supreme god Ra himself. He was the supreme representative of the religious as well as the political order. The king’s relationship to his subjects was thus also a spiritual relationship; the great god Ptah was in all living beings, so that the king was connected to the life-force (ka) of every individual. The king was revered as ‘greatest god’, the ‘perfect god’; he was said to have been conceived when Amun desired a royal wife, ‘the god’s wife’. The pharaoh ruled even over the netherworld as Osiris and ‘deceased father’. He was credited with the power of divine ‘utterance’, his word ‘became a reality immediately’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pharaoh-shephard&#34;&gt;Pharaoh, shephard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the Egyptians who introduced the metaphor of the king as shepherd into political thought. What they meant was that, just as a landowner entrusts his sheep to a shepherd, the god transmitted his authority and responsibility to the king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;kings-may-use-religion-but-they-cannot-invent-it&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Kings may use religion, but they cannot invent it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of religious monarchy in Egypt was brought to a strange climax in an attempted religious revolution by Amenhotep IV (1350–1334 BCE). He proclaimed the Aten (sun-disc) as sole god, and proclaimed himself the son of the Aten. He abolished the festivals and processions of all other gods, including the supreme Amun, systematically destroying their images, monuments, and inscriptions. The capital was transferred to a new city, Amarna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was also the first documented attempt to impose belief on a population by force. It did not outlast Amenhotep himself; the traditional religion was promptly restored. The memory of Amarna was so hated, and all traces of it so effectively obliterated, that the whole episode has only recently come to light. The priests eventually exercised their own kind of theocracy, with the high-priest acting on behalf of Amun. The god was now regarded as the real king. This was related to a growing belief that the god communicated important political decisions through oracles. By the time of Alexander’s conquest of Egypt in 331 BCE, ‘the Egyptian kingship faded into mere theory’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>