<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>babylon on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/babylon/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (babylon)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 04:36:52 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/babylon/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Transnational Diplomacy and Trade in 14th Century BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 04:36:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Region: West Asia and Mediterranean&lt;br&gt;
Time: 14th century BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This Late Bronze Age was an age of superpowers. The great pharaohs of the Eighteenth Dynasty had transformed Egypt into a conquering state, and the Hittites had created an empire out of the disparate city-states and kingdoms of Anatolia. The Assyrians controlled Near Eastern trade, and the Kassite kingdom of Babylonia remained a significant force in economic and military relationships. In addition to these imperial entities, numerous smaller states also flourished and extended their influence westward into the Mediterranean. Holding it all together was a network of trade routes that created an interdependent Afro-Eurasian world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational diplomacy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../amarna-letter-ea4/&#34;&gt;letters between rulers/elites&lt;/a&gt;, found in Akhenaten&amp;rsquo;s abandoned capital of Akhetaten (modern el-Amarna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marriage contracts between rulers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other lavish gifts (greeting gifts for festivals and such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptians delighted in Canaanite glass, Greeks prized Egyptian amulets, and the merchants of Syria admired Greek pottery and wool.
This was the background for the development of the abjad (the consonant-only family of alphabet later giving rise to the Phoenician alphabet). Ugarit, on the coast of modern-day Syria, developed the Ugaritic alphabet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:23:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By the rivers of Babylon, we sat and wept when we remembered Zion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There on the poplars we hung our harps,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For there our captors asked us for songs, our tormentors demanded songs of joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;They said, &amp;ldquo;Sing us one of the songs of Zion!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can we sing the songs of the Lord while in a foreign land?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I forget you, O Jerusalem, may my right hand forget its skill.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;May my tongue cling to the roof of my mouth if I do not remember you,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I do not consider Jerusalem my highest joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember, O Lord, what the Edomites did on the day Jerusalem fell.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tear it down,&amp;rdquo; they cried, &amp;ldquo;tear it down to its foundations!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;O Daughter of Babylon, doomed to destruction,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;happy is he who repays you for what you have done to us&amp;ndash;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He who seizes your infants and dashes them against the rocks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Psalm 137:1-9, NIV.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:12:56 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1200 - 1000 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelites-emergence-as-a-people/&#34;&gt;Israelites emerge as a distinct group of people&lt;/a&gt;, possibly organized in tribes or a league of tribes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kingship - first kings: Saul, then David, then Solomon, who built the temple of Jerusalem. After the death of Solomon, tensions between northern and southern tribes in Israel lead to the establishment of two separate kingdoms—the kingdom of Israel, composed of the ten northern tribes, with its capital eventually at Samaria, and the kingdom of Judah, composed of two southern tribes, with its capital at Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;721-722 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assyrians overrun the kingdom of Israel, deporting the ten tribes to the rest of the Assyrian Empire - lost forever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;586 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaldeans defeats Assyria, conquers the kingdom of Judah, destroys Jerusalem. Upper-class people from Jerusalem are deported to Babylon - Psalm 137 is their lament: &lt;a href=&#34;../babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/&#34;&gt;Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;539 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Babylon falls to Persian empire. The Persians destroy the Chaldean kingdom and allow the people of Judah to return to Jerusalem and rebuild their city and Temple. The revived kingdom of Judah remains under Persian control until the conquests of Alexander the Great in the fourth century B.C.E.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 05:09:01 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;3000 BCE: Emergence of Sumerian city-states&lt;br&gt;
2340 BCE: Sargon of Akkad overruns Sumerian city states, establishing Akkadian empire&lt;br&gt;
2100 BCE: Attacks from neighbouring hill peoples cause Akkadian empire to fall, bringing back independent city-states&lt;br&gt;
1792 BCE: Hammurabi&amp;rsquo;s rule from Babylon begins&lt;br&gt;
1754 BCE: Code of Hammurabi, a collection of 282 laws&lt;br&gt;
1750 BCE: Hammurabi&amp;rsquo;s rule ends&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>