<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>religion on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/religion/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (religion)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 07:24:07 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Judaism - God Outside Nature</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/judaism-god-outside-nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 07:24:07 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/judaism-god-outside-nature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This theology of Yahweh&amp;rsquo;s transcendence would later contribute to subsequent Western religions - the teaching that God is not part of nature but exists outside of it. God can therefore be understood, in purely intellectual or abstract terms, as entirely separate from the operations of the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eastern vs Western Religions</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/eastern-vs-western-religions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 04:39:36 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/eastern-vs-western-religions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Religions originating in monsoon Asia: Hinduism, Buddhism, Confucianism, Daoism, Shinto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;good-and-evil-in-the-world&#34;&gt;Good and Evil (in the world)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastern religions recognize that there is evil in the world, and even evil people, &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; none of them ever developed the sharp dualism between good and evil that is characteristic of Zoroastrianism, Judaism, Christianity and Islam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Indian and Chinese view, &lt;em&gt;all of creation is the work of God/Heaven&lt;/em&gt;, which thus necessarily includes both good and bad, or what is seen by humans as good or bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No conception of &amp;ldquo;originl sin&amp;rdquo; inherent in individuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Garden of Eden, no early innocence from which people fell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evil was understood as &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of God&amp;rsquo;s created world, not as some human aberration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;human-nature&#34;&gt;Human Nature&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic presumption of Eastern religions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are born and remain good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Misbehavior is a failure of &lt;em&gt;society&lt;/em&gt; which God creates imperfect OR of the individual straying from teaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are always redeemable through education or renewed efforts at right behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merit may be won by good deeds eg. charity - one does not have their sin &amp;ldquo;forgiven&amp;rdquo; by a priest or ritual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;attitude-to-the-natural-world&#34;&gt;Attitude to the Natural World&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastern religions accept the natural world as good, as part of a divine creation &lt;em&gt;greater and more powerful than humankind, but like humans, part of the cosmos&lt;/em&gt;. Nature is seen as a nurturing mother or an inspiring model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People occupy a humbler place in God&amp;rsquo;s creation -&amp;gt; hence &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; should adjust, while seeking the image of God in &lt;em&gt;nature&lt;/em&gt;, rather than themselves. &lt;strong&gt;Adapting to nature and understanding it are keys to earthly success and spiritual and moral truth&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;vs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Western religions&amp;rsquo; explicitly opposite attitude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book of Genesis calls the human world to &amp;ldquo;have dominion&amp;rdquo; over all the world of nature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19th and 20th century Western drive for the &amp;ldquo;conquest of nature&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could argue that Judaism was conceived in a harsher environment than the great Eastern religions.
See: &lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamia-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion&lt;/a&gt; - the environment in which Judaism was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Murphey, Rhoads. &lt;em&gt;A History of Asia&lt;/em&gt;. Routledge, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buddhism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/buddhism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:30 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/buddhism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two people key to its spread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;siddhartha-gautama&#34;&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born mid-sixth century BCE in the foothills of the Himalaya Mountains, in what is today southern Nepal, the son of a ruling kshatriya family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a family, left his family, meditated under a tree, achieved enlightenment, spent the rest of his life preaching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His ideas can be viewed as a reformist form of Brahmanism, designed to transfer responsibility from the priests to the individual, much as the sixteenth century German monk Martin Luther saw his ideas as a reformation of Christianity. Siddhartha accepted the concept of reincarnation and the role of karma as a means of influencing the movement of individual souls up and down the scale of life. Nirvana, the extinction of selfhood and reunion with the Great World Soul, is likened to a dreamless sleep, rather than the Christian concept of heavenly salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four noble truths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life is suffering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suffering is caused by desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end suffering is to end desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end desire is to avoid the extremes of a life of vulgar materialism and to follow the Middle Path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Middle Path: right knowledge, purpose, speech, conduct, occupation, effort, awareness, meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All human beings can aspire to Nirvana as a result of their behaviour in this life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siddharta Gautama died in 480 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ashoka&#34;&gt;Ashoka&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Converted to Buddhism in the third century BCE, and sent Buddhist missionaries throughout India, and ordered the erection of stone pillars with official edicts and Buddhist inscriptions to instruct people in the proper way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashoka died in 232 BCE, after which the Mauryan empire began to fragment into separate states - in 183 BCE, India reverted to disunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brahmanism - Overview</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/brahmanism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:21 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/brahmanism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the Rig Vedas, when Brahma, the supreme god, destroyed himself to create the four classes of the society, the &lt;em&gt;brahmins&lt;/em&gt; - the priest class - were made from his head, the &lt;em&gt;kshatriyas&lt;/em&gt; - the warrior, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-kingship&#34;&gt;king&lt;/a&gt;, administrator class - were made from his arms, the &lt;em&gt;vaishyas&lt;/em&gt; - the merchants - were made from his thighs, and the &lt;em&gt;sudras&lt;/em&gt; - the labourers and servants - came from the feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brahmins, kshatriya, vaishyas, are &lt;em&gt;twice-born&lt;/em&gt; - undergoing a ceremony at puberty whereby they&amp;rsquo;re initiated into adulthood and Indian society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:39:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social hierarchy: classical texts specified &lt;em&gt;varna&lt;/em&gt;, a system of four classes in society; this was instantiated into the caste system, &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;, where people are born into a clan (&lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;) that specifies social and economic duty, and requirements for endogamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s thought that this class system was introduced by the Aryans, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-history/&#34;&gt;when they first arrived in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophies that emerged from this background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview/&#34;&gt;Brahmanism&lt;/a&gt;, which later developed into Hinduism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of which were underwritten by the concept of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; - the sum/worth of one&amp;rsquo;s actions in life that decide one&amp;rsquo;s fate in their next life, and in brahmanism, this is accumulated through carrying out &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; - ethics, duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/&#34;&gt;Dharma vs. Artha, Morality vs. Practicality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 19:12:27 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Israelite monarchy’s greatest contribution to Jewish political thought was its failure. Military collapse demolished any strong theory of monarchy in Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of the Jewish community in exile in Babylon (6th century BCE) reinforced and transformed the sense of their uniqueness as a nation. They became a highly self-conscious community with a new conception of government and politics. The basis of the community was its religion and law. Kingship was now seen as an optional extra, a temporary and accidental feature of public life. In the sacred Jewish scriptures, kingship was presented as an alien graft, not part of the essential Israel, not an instrinsic part of its observance of the Law, nor of its worship of the one true god. They had learned to live, though not by choice—and, they hoped, not for long—as a stateless nation. To what extent they needed any form of governmental authority would be experienced and reflected upon over the ages, by Jews and then by others who associated themselves with this Jewish experience (notably, the early Christians and Shi’ite Muslims). Out of this came also anarchism and communism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:26 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gods-relationship-to-the-people&#34;&gt;God&amp;rsquo;s relationship to the people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental relationship was not between god and the king of Israel, but between god and the people of Israel. This was expressed as the covenant, originally between Yahweh and Abraham, including a pledge to his many descendants. I.e. it involved a &lt;em&gt;kinship group or race&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The individual recipients of the divine covenant are Abraham and Moses: great leaders, but long dead. The agreement with David is not called a ‘covenant’; it seems intended to add material about the state and royal dynasty, rather than as a recapitulation of what everyone knew to be the main body of the covenant, namely the Law. Rather, it was &lt;em&gt;the elders and the people who were the politically active agents at the time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main organizing force in Hebrew, and later Jewish, society was the law (ascribed to Yahweh) and the religious worship and ritual it prescribed; this Law had indeed been revealed to a historic leader, but he had transmitted it to the nation as a whole, not to a dynasty or institution. Hence divine legitimacy was bestowed not on the king but on the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, now positioned as the &lt;em&gt;primary political actor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;peoples-relationship-to-their-king&#34;&gt;People&amp;rsquo;s relationship to their king&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people were portrayed as playing a decisive part in the break-up of the kingdom of Israel and in the appointment of a rival king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was the people of the ten northern tribes of Israel that rejected Solomon&amp;rsquo;s designated heir, Rehoboam, and appointed Solomon&amp;rsquo;s younger son, Jeroboam (previously exiled by his father) as their king when they seceded from Judah.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘The men of Israel’ then ‘called [Jeroboam] to the assembly and made him king over the whole of Israel’. This was how Israel seceded from Judah, and from ‘the house of David’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people as compared to the king:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neither represent Yahweh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In matters of religious status and observances, the king was on a level with the people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The king could sometimes act as agent of the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; in a symbolic sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The king could be subjected to criticism for religious irregularities, or for failing to live up to the high standards of justice expected by legal and prophetic traditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;yahweh&#34;&gt;Yahweh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So high above all else that no king could claim to represent him - &amp;ldquo;politically unobtrusive&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did not need extravagant gifts which many of these hill people could ill afford anyway - no priestly class was necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ideological innovation on this scale was perhaps necessary [&amp;hellip;] to validate their new political identity, which separated them so radically from all other peoples. It enabled them to survive as the type of economic entity which they aspired to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re: Economic entity&lt;br&gt;
The Law stipulated that (rephrased) the &amp;ldquo;means of production (land, herds and flocks)&amp;rdquo; should be owned inalienably by extended families. The Jewish laws &amp;ldquo;inhibited social stratification&amp;rdquo; by eg. prohibiting interest on loans and the sale of land outside the family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Neo-Assyrian threat was the whetstone on which the Yahwist prophets sharpened their demands for an exclusive monotheism that went beyond monolatry. Hebrew prophets were practical political leaders as well as religious figures, and most of them understood that military resistance to the Neo-Assyrians was futile. So if the Hebrews were to survive as a people, they had to emphasize the one thing that separated them from everyone else in the known world: the worship of Yahweh and the denial of all other gods. The prophets’ insistence that Yahweh alone should be exalted was thus an aggressive reaction to the equally aggressive promotion of Assur by the Neo-Assyrians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:35:05 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Features that have shaped Israelite political thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Untouchably high God - implications for egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Covenant - implications for political power of people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Exile - implications for human condition and suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian vs Egyptian Kingship</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-vs-egyptian-kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 07:10:44 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-vs-egyptian-kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Never in Mesopotamia was his relationship with god so close as in Egypt; no Mesopotamian king was deified. In both cultures the image of the king as shepherd of the people was developed. The king’s duty to implement justice, especially by fair adjudication between the powerful and the weak, was emphasized in both cultures, perhaps more insistently in Egypt. The most striking contrast was the judicial and, occasionally, political role of citizens in Mesopotamia, and the complete absence of such popular participation in Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamia-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamia - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Egypt - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamia - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 07:07:11 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamia-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the language and concepts used, it seems clear that the gods had established not just individual rulers but an institution, with specific functions, which would outlast individual rulers—we can call this a state. It was symbolized by &lt;em&gt;‘sceptre, tiara and [shepherd’s] crook’&lt;/em&gt;; these ‘lay deposited before Anu in heaven’ before ‘kingship descended from heaven’. Among the fundamental cosmic and cultural essences were &lt;em&gt;‘the exalted and enduring crown, the throne of kingship, the exalted scepter, the royal insignia, the exalted shrine, shepherd-ship, kingship’&lt;/em&gt;. Kingship was bala; that is, ‘return or reversion to origin’, or ‘term of office’. This sounds like the prototype of the Irano-Islamic notion of the state (dawla). Thus, it seems, theology led, or enabled, people to formulate the abstract concept of an authority that would transcend the vagaries and misfortunes of individual monarchs, and so provide a more effective political instrument for human survival and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Egypt - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 06:32:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;pharaoh-god-king&#34;&gt;Pharaoh, god-king&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Egypt the king was more closely identified with the gods than in any other culture. He was the incarnation of Horus and Osiris, the son of the supreme god Ra himself. He was the supreme representative of the religious as well as the political order. The king’s relationship to his subjects was thus also a spiritual relationship; the great god Ptah was in all living beings, so that the king was connected to the life-force (ka) of every individual. The king was revered as ‘greatest god’, the ‘perfect god’; he was said to have been conceived when Amun desired a royal wife, ‘the god’s wife’. The pharaoh ruled even over the netherworld as Osiris and ‘deceased father’. He was credited with the power of divine ‘utterance’, his word ‘became a reality immediately’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pharaoh-shephard&#34;&gt;Pharaoh, shephard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the Egyptians who introduced the metaphor of the king as shepherd into political thought. What they meant was that, just as a landowner entrusts his sheep to a shepherd, the god transmitted his authority and responsibility to the king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;kings-may-use-religion-but-they-cannot-invent-it&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Kings may use religion, but they cannot invent it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of religious monarchy in Egypt was brought to a strange climax in an attempted religious revolution by Amenhotep IV (1350–1334 BCE). He proclaimed the Aten (sun-disc) as sole god, and proclaimed himself the son of the Aten. He abolished the festivals and processions of all other gods, including the supreme Amun, systematically destroying their images, monuments, and inscriptions. The capital was transferred to a new city, Amarna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was also the first documented attempt to impose belief on a population by force. It did not outlast Amenhotep himself; the traditional religion was promptly restored. The memory of Amarna was so hated, and all traces of it so effectively obliterated, that the whole episode has only recently come to light. The priests eventually exercised their own kind of theocracy, with the high-priest acting on behalf of Amun. The god was now regarded as the real king. This was related to a growing belief that the god communicated important political decisions through oracles. By the time of Alexander’s conquest of Egypt in 331 BCE, ‘the Egyptian kingship faded into mere theory’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Egypt - New Kingdom</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-new-kingdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 06:31:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/egypt-new-kingdom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the period of the New Kingdom, Egypt created an empire and became the most powerful state in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Kingdom: 1539 - 1069 BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18th to 20th dynasties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The power of the New Kingdom pharaohs was aided by massive wealth, which they showed by building new temples. Queen Hatshepsut (ca. 1503–1480 B.C.E.), one of the first women to become pharaoh in her own right, built a great temple at Deir el Bahri near Thebes. Hatshepsut was succeeded by her nephew, Thutmosis III (ca. 1480–1450 B.C.E.), who led seventeen military campaigns into Syria and Canaan and even reached the Euphrates River. Egyptian forces occupied Canaan and Syria and also moved westward into Libya.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amenhotep IV (1364 - 1347 BCE) and his wife Nefertiti introduced the worship of Aten, god of the sun disk, as the supreme god and later in his reign as the only god. He changed his name to Akhenaten (servant of Aten). Akhenaten’s preoccupation with his religious revolution caused him to ignore foreign affairs and led to the loss of both Syria and Canaan. Akhenaten’s changes were soon undone after his death by the boy-pharaoh Tutankhamun, who restored the old gods. The eighteenth dynasty soon came to an end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The nineteenth dynasty managed to restore Egyptian power one more time. Under Ramesses II (ca. 1279–1213 B.C.E.), the Egyptians regained control of Canaan, but new invasions in the thirteenth century by the “Sea Peoples,” as the Egyptians called them, destroyed Egyptian power in Canaan and drove the Egyptians back within their old frontiers. The days of Egyptian empire were ended, and the New Kingdom itself expired with the end of the twentieth dynasty in 1069 B.C.E. For the next thousand years, despite periodic revivals of strength, Egypt was dominated by Libyans, Nubians, Persians, and finally Macedonians after the conquest of Alexander the Great. In the first century B.C.E., Egypt became a province in Rome’s mighty empire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-old-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - Old Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../egypt-middle-kingdom/&#34;&gt;Egypt - Middle Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millenium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 03:21:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd millenium BCE – guilt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Personification of a man’s luck and ability to effectively think and act is identified with some known figure of the pantheon, usually a minor deity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sumerian composition: “Man and his God”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Man complains that what he knows does not come out right, what he says quite truthfully turns out to be false, he does things in all innocence and finds that he has been duped into committing wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His god – his powers of clear and fast thinking – is not there to suggest an answer when friends deceive him, or when evil-doers abuse him; his god has abandoned him and lost interest in him&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realization: blame lies with himself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plead: no man is perfect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He asks to be shown his faults, his transgressions, that he may confess them before his god and be forgiven; God is moved by his contrition and takes him back into favour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insight gained in the preceding millennium that the divine stands for, and upholds, a moral law -&amp;gt; is now bearing fruit in a realization of individual human responsibility, but also of innate human inability to live up to that responsibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 4th millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millenium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 03:20:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3rd millenium BCE – the sword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
As the settled areas of the country grew and joined, the protection that had been afforded by relative isolation was no longer there and fear of enemy attack, death or slavery, became a part of life ever present in the depth of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rise of great city-walls that around the towns in this period - the staggering amount of labor that must have gone into them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a shield against danger men looked to the now vitally important institutions of collective security, the great leagues and their officers, and particularly to the new institution of kingship as it took form and grew under the pressures of these years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gods, seen as kings and rulers, were no longer powers in nature only, they became powers in human affairs – in history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 4th millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mesopotamian religion - 4th millenium BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 01:39:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/mesopotamian-religion-4th-millenium-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4th millenium BCE – famine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The powers to whom they turned were powers in and behind their primary economics on which life depended: fishing, herding, agriculture, as even the briefest look at the character of the chief gods of their cities will show. Aim and purpose of their cults were to insure the presence of these essential powers for fertility produce, and food. Houses – temples – were built for them so that they might dwell with men as members of the human community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i.e. ziggurats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this seems to be true of egyptian temples as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jacobsen, Thorkild. &amp;ldquo;Ancient Mesopotamian Religion: The Central Concerns.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society,&lt;/em&gt; Vol. 107, No. 6, Cuneiform Studies and the History of Civilization (Dec. 20, 1963), pp. 473-484&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-2nd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 2nd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../mesopotamian-religion-3rd-millenium-bce/&#34;&gt;Mesopotamian religion - 3rd millenium BCE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>