<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bronze age on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/bronze-age/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (bronze age)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 04:36:52 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/bronze-age/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Transnational Diplomacy and Trade in 14th Century BCE</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 04:36:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/transnational-diplomacy-and-trade-in-14th-century-bce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Region: West Asia and Mediterranean&lt;br&gt;
Time: 14th century BCE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This Late Bronze Age was an age of superpowers. The great pharaohs of the Eighteenth Dynasty had transformed Egypt into a conquering state, and the Hittites had created an empire out of the disparate city-states and kingdoms of Anatolia. The Assyrians controlled Near Eastern trade, and the Kassite kingdom of Babylonia remained a significant force in economic and military relationships. In addition to these imperial entities, numerous smaller states also flourished and extended their influence westward into the Mediterranean. Holding it all together was a network of trade routes that created an interdependent Afro-Eurasian world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational diplomacy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../amarna-letter-ea4/&#34;&gt;letters between rulers/elites&lt;/a&gt;, found in Akhenaten&amp;rsquo;s abandoned capital of Akhetaten (modern el-Amarna)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marriage contracts between rulers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;other lavish gifts (greeting gifts for festivals and such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence of transnational trade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptians delighted in Canaanite glass, Greeks prized Egyptian amulets, and the merchants of Syria admired Greek pottery and wool.
This was the background for the development of the abjad (the consonant-only family of alphabet later giving rise to the Phoenician alphabet). Ugarit, on the coast of modern-day Syria, developed the Ugaritic alphabet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>