<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>buddhism on Notetaking</title>
    <link>/tags/buddhism/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (buddhism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:30 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/tags/buddhism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Buddhism - Overview</title>
      <link>/posts/buddhism-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:54:30 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/buddhism-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two people key to its spread:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ashoka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;siddhartha-gautama&#34;&gt;Siddhartha Gautama&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born mid-sixth century BCE in the foothills of the Himalaya Mountains, in what is today southern Nepal, the son of a ruling kshatriya family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a family, left his family, meditated under a tree, achieved enlightenment, spent the rest of his life preaching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His ideas can be viewed as a reformist form of Brahmanism, designed to transfer responsibility from the priests to the individual, much as the sixteenth century German monk Martin Luther saw his ideas as a reformation of Christianity. Siddhartha accepted the concept of reincarnation and the role of karma as a means of influencing the movement of individual souls up and down the scale of life. Nirvana, the extinction of selfhood and reunion with the Great World Soul, is likened to a dreamless sleep, rather than the Christian concept of heavenly salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four noble truths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life is suffering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suffering is caused by desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end suffering is to end desire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way to end desire is to avoid the extremes of a life of vulgar materialism and to follow the Middle Path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Middle Path: right knowledge, purpose, speech, conduct, occupation, effort, awareness, meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All human beings can aspire to Nirvana as a result of their behaviour in this life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siddharta Gautama died in 480 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ashoka&#34;&gt;Ashoka&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Converted to Buddhism in the third century BCE, and sent Buddhist missionaries throughout India, and ordered the erection of stone pillars with official edicts and Buddhist inscriptions to instruct people in the proper way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashoka died in 232 BCE, after which the Mauryan empire began to fragment into separate states - in 183 BCE, India reverted to disunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-state-and-religion/&#34;&gt;Ancient India - State and Religion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient India State and Religion</title>
      <link>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 23:39:16 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ancient-india-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social hierarchy: classical texts specified &lt;em&gt;varna&lt;/em&gt;, a system of four classes in society; this was instantiated into the caste system, &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;, where people are born into a clan (&lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt;) that specifies social and economic duty, and requirements for endogamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s thought that this class system was introduced by the Aryans, &lt;a href=&#34;../ancient-india-history/&#34;&gt;when they first arrived in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophies that emerged from this background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../brahmanism-overview/&#34;&gt;Brahmanism&lt;/a&gt;, which later developed into Hinduism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../buddhism-overview/&#34;&gt;Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of which were underwritten by the concept of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; - the sum/worth of one&amp;rsquo;s actions in life that decide one&amp;rsquo;s fate in their next life, and in brahmanism, this is accumulated through carrying out &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; - ethics, duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../dharma-vs-artha-morality-vs-practicality/&#34;&gt;Dharma vs. Artha, Morality vs. Practicality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>