<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>israel on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/israel/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (israel)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 07:24:07 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/israel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Judaism - God Outside Nature</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/judaism-god-outside-nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 07:24:07 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/judaism-god-outside-nature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This theology of Yahweh&amp;rsquo;s transcendence would later contribute to subsequent Western religions - the teaching that God is not part of nature but exists outside of it. God can therefore be understood, in purely intellectual or abstract terms, as entirely separate from the operations of the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelites - Emergence as a People</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelites-emergence-as-a-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 07:00:47 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelites-emergence-as-a-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to the Book of Judges, the Hebrews were herdsmen who had just begun to establish permanent settlements around the time of the Philistines&amp;rsquo; arrival in the Levant. They had organized themselves into twelve tribes - extended clan units whose families owed one another mutual aid and protection in times of war, but who frequently fought over cattle and grazing rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the middle of 1200 BCE, these tribes occupied two major territories: Judah in the south, Israel in the North.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Philistines conquered the Levantine coast around 1050 BCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 1025 BCE, an influential tribal judge called Samuel selected a king, Saul, to lead Hebrew resistance against the Philistines. (However, Saul proved to be an ineffective war leader, blocking further intrusion but not ousting the Philistines from the valleys/coastal plains, hence Samuel withdrew his support and threw it behind a young warrior in Saul&amp;rsquo;s entourage, Saul&amp;rsquo;s son-in-law, David.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt;. 18th ed. ,W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-kingship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 19:12:27 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-kingship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Israelite monarchy’s greatest contribution to Jewish political thought was its failure. Military collapse demolished any strong theory of monarchy in Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of the Jewish community in exile in Babylon (6th century BCE) reinforced and transformed the sense of their uniqueness as a nation. They became a highly self-conscious community with a new conception of government and politics. The basis of the community was its religion and law. Kingship was now seen as an optional extra, a temporary and accidental feature of public life. In the sacred Jewish scriptures, kingship was presented as an alien graft, not part of the essential Israel, not an instrinsic part of its observance of the Law, nor of its worship of the one true god. They had learned to live, though not by choice—and, they hoped, not for long—as a stateless nation. To what extent they needed any form of governmental authority would be experienced and reflected upon over the ages, by Jews and then by others who associated themselves with this Jewish experience (notably, the early Christians and Shi’ite Muslims). Out of this came also anarchism and communism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:42 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The conviction that they had been chosen by the only god that exists went through its most crucial test in the Exile &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;../babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/&#34;&gt;see: lament&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;. Conquest and exile interacted with the core Jewish tenet of the chosen people, destined by Yahweh for the lead role among all the peoples of the world. This gave rise to a new genre of prophecy, initiated by Jeremiah even while the monarchical state was in the process of collapsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What emerged was a consolidation and reinterpretation of what had gone before. [&amp;hellip;] Defeat and suffering were interpreted as divine retribution for moral and legal transgressions, sin codified as central to the divine scheme. They were suffering the consequences of neglecting their side of the covenant with Yahweh. But—and here was the new emphasis—Yahweh was a merciful and wise god: he would use their sin and suffering to teach his people—&lt;em&gt;and through them all human beings&lt;/em&gt;—a new way of thought and practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of this [&amp;hellip;came&amp;hellip;] central ideas about the divine nature and the human condition. Defeat and disaster were explained in terms not, as in the Greek historians, of human expectations, interests, and conflicts, but in terms of a divine design for humanity. They created &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; counter-culture of the oppressed, making themselves superior in the divine scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was more than this: Jeremiah prophesied a new covenant in which Yahweh would give the people ‘law within them and write it on their hearts&amp;hellip;No longer need they teach one another to know the Lord; all of them, high and low alike, shall know me’ (Jer. 31: 31–4). This was a revolution within a revolution: it meant, obviously, that every individual Israelite would know Yahweh for himself/herself. The law was internalized. The implication of this for individualism and democracy are prodigious and clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israeite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:26 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;gods-relationship-to-the-people&#34;&gt;God&amp;rsquo;s relationship to the people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental relationship was not between god and the king of Israel, but between god and the people of Israel. This was expressed as the covenant, originally between Yahweh and Abraham, including a pledge to his many descendants. I.e. it involved a &lt;em&gt;kinship group or race&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The individual recipients of the divine covenant are Abraham and Moses: great leaders, but long dead. The agreement with David is not called a ‘covenant’; it seems intended to add material about the state and royal dynasty, rather than as a recapitulation of what everyone knew to be the main body of the covenant, namely the Law. Rather, it was &lt;em&gt;the elders and the people who were the politically active agents at the time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main organizing force in Hebrew, and later Jewish, society was the law (ascribed to Yahweh) and the religious worship and ritual it prescribed; this Law had indeed been revealed to a historic leader, but he had transmitted it to the nation as a whole, not to a dynasty or institution. Hence divine legitimacy was bestowed not on the king but on the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, now positioned as the &lt;em&gt;primary political actor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;peoples-relationship-to-their-king&#34;&gt;People&amp;rsquo;s relationship to their king&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people were portrayed as playing a decisive part in the break-up of the kingdom of Israel and in the appointment of a rival king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was the people of the ten northern tribes of Israel that rejected Solomon&amp;rsquo;s designated heir, Rehoboam, and appointed Solomon&amp;rsquo;s younger son, Jeroboam (previously exiled by his father) as their king when they seceded from Judah.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘The men of Israel’ then ‘called [Jeroboam] to the assembly and made him king over the whole of Israel’. This was how Israel seceded from Judah, and from ‘the house of David’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people as compared to the king:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neither represent Yahweh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In matters of religious status and observances, the king was on a level with the people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The king could sometimes act as agent of the &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; in a symbolic sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The king could be subjected to criticism for religious irregularities, or for failing to live up to the high standards of justice expected by legal and prophetic traditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israelite Political Thinking - God and Egalitarianism</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 18:52:09 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;yahweh&#34;&gt;Yahweh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So high above all else that no king could claim to represent him - &amp;ldquo;politically unobtrusive&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did not need extravagant gifts which many of these hill people could ill afford anyway - no priestly class was necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ideological innovation on this scale was perhaps necessary [&amp;hellip;] to validate their new political identity, which separated them so radically from all other peoples. It enabled them to survive as the type of economic entity which they aspired to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re: Economic entity&lt;br&gt;
The Law stipulated that (rephrased) the &amp;ldquo;means of production (land, herds and flocks)&amp;rdquo; should be owned inalienably by extended families. The Jewish laws &amp;ldquo;inhibited social stratification&amp;rdquo; by eg. prohibiting interest on loans and the sale of land outside the family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Neo-Assyrian threat was the whetstone on which the Yahwist prophets sharpened their demands for an exclusive monotheism that went beyond monolatry. Hebrew prophets were practical political leaders as well as religious figures, and most of them understood that military resistance to the Neo-Assyrians was futile. So if the Hebrews were to survive as a people, they had to emphasize the one thing that separated them from everyone else in the known world: the worship of Yahweh and the denial of all other gods. The prophets’ insistence that Yahweh alone should be exalted was thus an aggressive reaction to the equally aggressive promotion of Assur by the Neo-Assyrians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.
Cole, Joshua and Carol Symes. &lt;em&gt;Western Civilizations&lt;/em&gt; 18th ed., W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-kingship/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Kingship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Covenant and the People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Israelite Political Thinking - Exile and Suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel - State and Religion</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:35:05 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-state-and-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Features that have shaped Israelite political thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-god-egalitarianism/&#34;&gt;Untouchably high God - implications for egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-covenant-people/&#34;&gt;Covenant - implications for political power of people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelite-political-thinking-exile-suffering/&#34;&gt;Exile - implications for human condition and suffering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Black, Anthony. &lt;em&gt;A World History of Ancient Political Thought&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:23:48 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By the rivers of Babylon, we sat and wept when we remembered Zion.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There on the poplars we hung our harps,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For there our captors asked us for songs, our tormentors demanded songs of joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;They said, &amp;ldquo;Sing us one of the songs of Zion!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can we sing the songs of the Lord while in a foreign land?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I forget you, O Jerusalem, may my right hand forget its skill.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;May my tongue cling to the roof of my mouth if I do not remember you,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I do not consider Jerusalem my highest joy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remember, O Lord, what the Edomites did on the day Jerusalem fell.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tear it down,&amp;rdquo; they cried, &amp;ldquo;tear it down to its foundations!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;O Daughter of Babylon, doomed to destruction,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;happy is he who repays you for what you have done to us&amp;ndash;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He who seizes your infants and dashes them against the rocks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Psalm 137:1-9, NIV.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel History</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 17:12:56 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/israel-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1200 - 1000 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../israelites-emergence-as-a-people/&#34;&gt;Israelites emerge as a distinct group of people&lt;/a&gt;, possibly organized in tribes or a league of tribes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kingship - first kings: Saul, then David, then Solomon, who built the temple of Jerusalem. After the death of Solomon, tensions between northern and southern tribes in Israel lead to the establishment of two separate kingdoms—the kingdom of Israel, composed of the ten northern tribes, with its capital eventually at Samaria, and the kingdom of Judah, composed of two southern tribes, with its capital at Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;721-722 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assyrians overrun the kingdom of Israel, deporting the ten tribes to the rest of the Assyrian Empire - lost forever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;586 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaldeans defeats Assyria, conquers the kingdom of Judah, destroys Jerusalem. Upper-class people from Jerusalem are deported to Babylon - Psalm 137 is their lament: &lt;a href=&#34;../babylonian-captivity-psalm-137/&#34;&gt;Babylonian Captivity - Psalm 137&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;539 BCE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Babylon falls to Persian empire. The Persians destroy the Chaldean kingdom and allow the people of Judah to return to Jerusalem and rebuild their city and Temple. The revived kingdom of Judah remains under Persian control until the conquests of Alexander the Great in the fourth century B.C.E.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Duiker, William, and Jackson Spielvogel. &lt;em&gt;The Essential World History&lt;/em&gt;. Cengage Learning, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>