<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>copper on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/copper/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (copper)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 10:17:45 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/copper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Copper</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 10:17:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/copper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The element takes its Latin name - &lt;em&gt;cuprum&lt;/em&gt; - from the island Cyprus, which provided most of the copper for Bronze Age craftsmen in the Mediterranean, Egypt and Mesopotamia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;deposition&#34;&gt;Deposition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along mid-ocean spreading ridges - when hot magma is close to the surface, seawater enters the cracks, becomes superheated, and surges back up through the crust, leaching minerals out of the surrounding rock as it goes up into hydrothermal vents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the name &amp;ldquo;black smokers&amp;rdquo;, referring to the precipitation of zinc, lead, gold, silver, manganese, suphides&amp;hellip; COPPER, cobalt, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cyprus&#34;&gt;Cyprus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility of copper on Cyprus due to a slice of ocenic crust that became beached on top of the continental, created in a spreading rift in the Tethys Sea ~90 mya and scooped up on top of Cyprus with the closure of the Tethys as Africa pushed up into Eurasia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the second millennium BC Cyprus became the major supplier of copper to Mesopotamia, Egypt and the Mediterranean world. As we have seen, in the Bronze Age charcoal was used to bake the metal out of its ore in copper smelting furnaces, and so Cyprus’s productivity also depended on a large supply of timber. In fact, by studying the 4 million tonnes of slag heaps on the island that were dumped as waste once the copper metal had been extracted from the mined rock, archaeologists have been able to calculate how much timber was required. It turns out that throughout the 3,000 years of copper production on Cyprus, the entire area of pine forests covering the plains and the mountainsides of the island would need to have been cleared at least sixteen times over – an early example of sustainable woodland management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(but the same subduction boundary that created the copper deposits on Cyprus runs past Crete, creating Thera (modern day Santorini), hence the eruption between 1600-1500 BCE.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-copper-deposits&#34;&gt;Other copper deposits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rio Tinto in Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noranda in Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ural Mountains in Russia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Dartnell, Lewis. &lt;em&gt;Origins: How the Earth Made Us&lt;/em&gt;. Basic Books, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>