<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tethys on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/tethys/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (tethys)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 10:17:45 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/tethys/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Copper</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 10:17:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/copper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The element takes its Latin name - &lt;em&gt;cuprum&lt;/em&gt; - from the island Cyprus, which provided most of the copper for Bronze Age craftsmen in the Mediterranean, Egypt and Mesopotamia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;deposition&#34;&gt;Deposition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along mid-ocean spreading ridges - when hot magma is close to the surface, seawater enters the cracks, becomes superheated, and surges back up through the crust, leaching minerals out of the surrounding rock as it goes up into hydrothermal vents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence the name &amp;ldquo;black smokers&amp;rdquo;, referring to the precipitation of zinc, lead, gold, silver, manganese, suphides&amp;hellip; COPPER, cobalt, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cyprus&#34;&gt;Cyprus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility of copper on Cyprus due to a slice of ocenic crust that became beached on top of the continental, created in a spreading rift in the Tethys Sea ~90 mya and scooped up on top of Cyprus with the closure of the Tethys as Africa pushed up into Eurasia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the second millennium BC Cyprus became the major supplier of copper to Mesopotamia, Egypt and the Mediterranean world. As we have seen, in the Bronze Age charcoal was used to bake the metal out of its ore in copper smelting furnaces, and so Cyprus’s productivity also depended on a large supply of timber. In fact, by studying the 4 million tonnes of slag heaps on the island that were dumped as waste once the copper metal had been extracted from the mined rock, archaeologists have been able to calculate how much timber was required. It turns out that throughout the 3,000 years of copper production on Cyprus, the entire area of pine forests covering the plains and the mountainsides of the island would need to have been cleared at least sixteen times over – an early example of sustainable woodland management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(but the same subduction boundary that created the copper deposits on Cyprus runs past Crete, creating Thera (modern day Santorini), hence the eruption between 1600-1500 BCE.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-copper-deposits&#34;&gt;Other copper deposits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rio Tinto in Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noranda in Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ural Mountains in Russia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Dartnell, Lewis. &lt;em&gt;Origins: How the Earth Made Us&lt;/em&gt;. Basic Books, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limestone</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/limestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 07:44:25 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/limestone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Limestone: calcium carbonate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;oolitic-limestone&#34;&gt;Oolitic limestone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly formed during the Jurassic Period, as warm, shallow seas flooded the land. Calcium carbonate from the shells of sea creatures eg. foraminifera precipitated as a limy mud, and as particles rolled back and forth around the seabed with tidal currents, becoming coated with concentric layers of this calcite mineral, they form balls called ooliths, which are then cemented together with more calcite to form oolitic limestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deposits found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;across Britain in a great sash from East Yorkshire, through Cotswolds, down to the Dorset coast. Oxford, in the middle of this band, has many of its colleges built out of this stone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isle of Portland, a promontory jutting out into the English channel, where it was laid down 150 million years ago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southern Indiana, where it was laid down earlier than Portland stone, in the early Carboniferous period 340 million years ago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;nummulitic-limestone&#34;&gt;Nummulitic limestone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Made out of shells of giant foraminifera called &lt;em&gt;nummulites&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deposits found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Across a huge area from Northern Europe to Middle East to North Africa and SE Asia eg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nile, where they were used to build pyramids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This expansive region of nummulitic limestone was laid down in the warm, shallow margins of the Tethys Ocean, 40–50 million years ago. During this period of the early Eocene, global temperatures were elevated, and the high sea levels caused the Tethys Ocean to flood in great arms stretching to Northern Europe and across North Africa. Huge numbers of forams lived in the warm waters, and when they died great drifts of their coin-shaped shells made of calcium carbonate sank down and carpeted the seafloor. Over time, they became cemented together to form the nummulitic limestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;travertine&#34;&gt;Travertine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precipitates out of solution when water from hot springs cools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deposits found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tibur (modern day Tivoli, NE of Rome), where it was used for the main pillars and external walls of the Colosseum in Rome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;marble&#34;&gt;Marble&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metamorphosized limestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples:
Northern Mediterranean coastline - where this Tethyean limestone has been baked underground in the convergent plate boundaries around the Mediterranean – by magma rising up and intruding into it, or by its being caught in the tectonic vice crunching up mountain ranges like the Alps – it is metamorphosed into marble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence also its use as the signature stone of Classical Greek and Roman sculpture, monuments, and grand public buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deposits found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The city of Carrara, in northern Tuscany. This marble was used to built the Pantheon and Trajan&amp;rsquo;s Column, and was a favourite of Renaissance sculptors - eg. Michelangelo&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;David&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chalk&#34;&gt;Chalk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signature of the Cretaceous Period (100-66 mya) - &lt;em&gt;creta&lt;/em&gt; in Latin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deposits found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southern England: most clearly visible on the South Coast, where it forms the eye-catching White Cliffs of Dover. It continues under the English Channel to France, where it has produced mirror-image white cliffs and provided the terroir of the great French wine regions of Champagne, Chablis and Sancerre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Dartnell, Lewis. &lt;em&gt;Origins: How the Earth Made Us&lt;/em&gt;. Basic Books, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>