<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>steel on Notetaking</title>
    <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/steel/</link>
    <description>Notetaking (steel)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 11:01:13 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/tags/steel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Steel</title>
      <link>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/steel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 11:01:13 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bathrobe-enthusiast.github.io/notes/posts/steel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steel: an alloy of iron with a small amount of carbon, typically 1% or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;importance&#34;&gt;Importance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Properties vary with carbon %: low-carbon steel is soft but tough, high-carbon steel is hard but brittle. In the early years, wrought iron was cooked with charcoal to absorb carbon, or wrought and cast iron were mixed to adjust proportions; high0quality steel remained laborious to create and was reserved for critical applications eg. cutting edge of knives/swords, springs in clocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;development&#34;&gt;Development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-current-age-of-cheap-mass-produced-steel-began-in-the-1850s-with-the-development-of-a-simple-way-to-remove-carbon-from-pig-iron&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Our current age of cheap, mass-produced steel began in the 1850s with the development of a simple way to remove carbon from pig iron.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the US, post-Civil War, railroads were the largest single employer of labour. Railroad expansion meant a greater need for coal, iron, and later steel, to build railroad cars and lay track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The steel industry was a catalyst for a host of other industries; in 1859, the value of US manufactured goods was $1.9 billion, but by 1899 it had risen to $13 billion with the rise of industrial giants like Carnegie Steel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Dartnell, Lewis. &lt;em&gt;Origins: How the Earth Made Us&lt;/em&gt;. Basic Books, 2019.
Murrin, John M., et al. &lt;em&gt;Liberty, Equality, Power: A History of the American People&lt;/em&gt;. 6th ed., Cengage Learning, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>